<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands vvarning by Germanies vvoe: or, An historicall narration, of the originall, progresse, tenets, names, and severall sects of the Anabaptists, in Germany, and the Low Countries: continued for about one hundred and twenty years, from anno 1521. (which was the time of their first rise,) until these dayes. VVherein is set forth their severall errors dangerous, and very destructive to the peace both of church and state: the way and manner of their spreading them: the many great commotions: (yea,to the effusion of much blood,) which they occasioned in those parts, by their opposition to, and resistance of the civill magistrates; and what course there was taken for the suppressing them. / By Frederick Spanhemius, Doctor, and Professor of Divinity, in the Vniversity of Leyden in Holland. Published according to order.</title>
            <author>Spanheim, Friedrich, 1600-1649.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4798</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E362_28</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861756</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113900</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113900)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 58:E362[28])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands vvarning by Germanies vvoe: or, An historicall narration, of the originall, progresse, tenets, names, and severall sects of the Anabaptists, in Germany, and the Low Countries: continued for about one hundred and twenty years, from anno 1521. (which was the time of their first rise,) until these dayes. VVherein is set forth their severall errors dangerous, and very destructive to the peace both of church and state: the way and manner of their spreading them: the many great commotions: (yea,to the effusion of much blood,) which they occasioned in those parts, by their opposition to, and resistance of the civill magistrates; and what course there was taken for the suppressing them. / By Frederick Spanhemius, Doctor, and Professor of Divinity, in the Vniversity of Leyden in Holland. Published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Spanheim, Friedrich, 1600-1649.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Dever &amp; Robert Ibbitson, for John Bellamie, at the three Golden Lions in Corn-hill, neere the Royall Exhange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nou: 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Anabaptists --  Germany --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Anabaptists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113900:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ENGLANDS</hi> VVARNING BY GERMANIES WOE: OR, An Hiſtoricall Narration, of the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, Progreſſe, Tenets, Names, and ſeverall Sects of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and the Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries: Continued for about one hundred and twenty years, from <hi>Anno</hi> 1521. (which was the time of their firſt Riſe,) untill theſe Dayes.</p>
            <p>VVherin is ſet forth their ſeverall Errors dangerous, and very deſtructive to the Peace both of Church and State: The way and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their ſpreading them: The many great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions: (yea, to the effuſion of much blood,) which they occaſioned in thoſe parts, by their oppoſition to, and reſiſtance of the Civill Magiſtrates; And what courſe was there taken for the ſuppreſſing them.</p>
            <p>By FREDERICK SPANHEMIUS, <hi>Doctor, and Profeſſour of Divinity, in the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of</hi> Leyden <hi>in</hi> Holland.</p>
            <p>Foelix quem faciunt aeliena pericula cautum.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>John Dever</hi> &amp; <hi>Robert Ibbitſon,</hi> for <hi>John Bellamie,</hi> at the three <hi>Golden Lions</hi> in <hi>Corn-hill,</hi> neere the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113900:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113900:2"/>
            <head>Englands warning by Germanies Woe, <hi>OR,</hi> An Hiſtoricall Narration, of the Originall, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe, Tenets, Names, and ſeverall Sects of the Anabaptiſts in Germany, and the low Countryes.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Originall, or beginning of the Anabaptiſts.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Urpoſing by the aſſiſtance of God,<note place="margin">The Proem.</note> for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vindication of the truth, to diſpute againſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> for the more full illuſtration of the matter I have taken in hand; I thought fit briefly to praemiſe theſe things. 1 <hi>Of the Originall of theſe Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaries.</hi> 2 <hi>Of their Progreſſe.</hi> 3 <hi>Of the divers Sects into which they are divided.</hi> 4 <hi>Of the Names by which they are commonly called.</hi> 5 <hi>Of their Heterodox opinions.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt: namely, the Originall, or beginning of this ſort of men, which are moſt commonly termed <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> Their firſt birth is challenged by the yeare of our Lord, 1521. when they began to appeare on the ſtage, and to enter into theſe parts of the Chriſtian world. Thoſe that are read to be the firſt, which helped the world to be delivered of this Sect; were <hi>Nicholas Storch, Marcus Stubner,</hi> and chiefly, one <hi>Thomas Muntzer,</hi> men borne in upper-Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many; <hi>whoſe pretence was piety, of a civill life in appearance; but their mindes greedy after innovations, ambitious of Honour, and made and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for ungodly enterpriſes.</hi> To their deſignes a while joyned himſelfe <hi>Martinus Cellarius,</hi> a Swede by Nation, diſciple of <hi>Capnion,</hi> and one of <hi>Melanchtoms</hi> familiars; but who afterwards, both by his and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> admonition, repented; and together with his Sect caſt of his Country name, taking unto him from thence-forth the name of <hi>Borrhai;</hi> under which name he was firſt placed in the profeſſion of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113900:3"/>Philoſophy, and afterwards of Divinity, in the famous Univerſity of <hi>Bazill;</hi> where (beſides his writings in Logicke and Mathematicks) by publiſhing Commentaries upon ſome Books of the old Teſtament, he commended himſelfe unto the Church of God; untill at laſt being ſeized by the Peſtilence, he there finiſhed his life, in the Communion of the Orthodox Church, the yeare of our Lord. 1564.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicholas Storch,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Stubner,</hi> by divers practiſes indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to draw the heedleſſe people after them; this latter by the fame of his learning and a certaine dexterity he had in expounding the holy Scripture; the former (as being altogether unlearned,) by his popular eloquence, and report of inſpirations, revelations and ſecret conferences with God; both by a great deale of jugling and divers frauds. Theſe notwithſtanding proceeded more warily and gently; but more violently and furiouſly <hi>Thomas Muntzer,</hi> under whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct brake forth that lamentable ſedition of the Country-men, by which in the former age, upper-Germany was ſo grievouſly ſhaken, and with the ſame, the fruites of that new Goſpell, where-with <hi>Storch</hi> and <hi>Stubner</hi> had poſſeſſed the mindes of the common people. The reſidue of both whoſe lives, and their ends, are uncertaine. Of <hi>Muntzers</hi> further enterpriſes comes now particularly to be ſpoken.</p>
               <p>Some fanaticke ſpirits take occaſion of making parties, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Church of God, upon the words of <hi>Luther,</hi> in his Booke of Chriſtian liberty, which is extant amongſt his workes in the third Tome: and was firſt publiſhed in the yeare of our Lord, 1520. ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving read there, <hi>that a Chriſtian man is Lord of all things, and ſubject to none:</hi> which words written by <hi>Luther</hi> that eminent ſervant of God in the beſt part, and largely expounded; and by a contrary aphoriſme, (namely that the ſame was ſervant of all, and ſubject to all,) more fully declared; were wreſted to an ill ſenſe by men impatient both of their owne and others quietneſſe: who upon that occaſion, firſt pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately, and afterward publiquely, began to ſpeake evill of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Princes unto the people; telling them of their exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and boaſting the liberty purchaſed to all under the Kingdome of Chriſt; and making large complaints, not onely of the Tyranny of the Pope of Rome, but alſo of many faults ſtill tolerated in the Church by the firſt reformers: and ſo ſhaking the two pillars of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique order, the dignity of the Magiſtrate, and the reverence of the ſacred Miniſtery, and the authority of both. Thereupon conſulted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113900:3"/>framing a new and more perfect Church, and concerning its new policy; and on this occaſion thought of a new Baptiſme to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itiate the diſciples thereof. But leaſt the reverence of the Baptiſme formerly received, ſhould be any hinderance to their purpoſe; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Baptiſme was exclaimed againſt as vaine, yea, unlawfull, being conferred upon Infants, which were uncapable thereof; whereas this Sacrament ought to be adminiſtred to none but men growne, and who had the uſe of their will and reaſon. And that the zeale of this new Church, which theſe Doctors deſired to raiſe out of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh, might the more deeply enter into the mindes of the common people; they tooke ſpeciall care to make great ſhew of piety them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to preſſe the ſame upon others. Hence the ordinary ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of publique Sermons, and private Conventicles was. That wee muſt deteſt ſinne, ſuddue the fleſh, ſtirre up the ſpirit, exerciſe duties of charity, beare the Croſſe of Chriſt, give our ſelves to faſting, bee plaine in apparell, moderate in dyet, compoſe the dreſſing of our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes to neglect, rather then ornament, and be ſparing of ſpeech. It cannot be ſaid, how much the enemy of mankinde, by this ſlight transforming himſelfe into an Angell of light, and hiding the depths of Satan, advanced his cauſe; and how much this meere out-ſide of godlineſſe and holineſſe made the mindes of men not evill addicted unto theſe new Evangeliſts.</p>
               <p>The mindes of men being thus prepared; <hi>Thomas Muntzer,</hi> firſt Paſtor of <hi>Cygnea,</hi> afterwards of <hi>Alſtet,</hi> a Towne ſeated in the limits of <hi>Thuringia</hi> and <hi>Saxony,</hi> thinking he might now go on with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, hardned himſelfe in his audacious wickedneſſe; yea, reſolved in his minde to adventure on any miſchiefe whatſoever. For when he obſerved the name of <hi>Luther</hi> to be famous every where, for reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Churches liberty, and all mens mindes to be inclined towards him: he thought he muſt by ſome notable enterprize get himſelfe a name amongſt all men likewiſe; and to this end was ſo bold, as to profeſſe that he would reſtore the politicke or (as ſometimes he uſed to call it) naturall liberty; and deliver ſubjects from their yoke, and Tyranny, ſo did this contemner of Gods ordinance ſtile the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Princes and Magiſtrates: But when he could not get <hi>Luther</hi> to joyne with him, nor prove his fact to be lawfull unto him, with whom he had often meetings thereabout, at <hi>Wittenberg:</hi> but on the contrary was rebuked by him, and earneſtly admoniſhed not to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113900:4"/>the publique peace, yea, to ſubmit to the order which God had ordained; he began to riſe up, and thunder againſt <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe, crying out, that <hi>Luther</hi> was as much in fault as the Pope of Rome; that it was true, the worke of reformation was ſomething furthered by him, but left ſtill infected with much leaven; yea, that <hi>Luther</hi> was worſe then the Pope, for that he had publiſhed onely a carnall Goſpell. Neither left he to exclaime againſt the Tyranny of the Civill Magiſtrate to the utmoſt, nor to preſſe upon the common people, that all things by nature were free and common; and that the yoke of Princes was as much to be caſt off as the Popes of Rome: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faire warning was not like to prevaile with them, but they would have both the goods and lives of their ſubjects to be tribute to their luſts; it was moſt juſt that every one ſeeke to recover that by force of Armes, which God would have to be common to all. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons being ſtirred up by this Trumpet, and inticed with the ſeeming ſweetneſſe of a certaine new liberty, began every where to imbroyle themſelves in dangerous mutinies. Neere the River <hi>Acronius</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roares are made; in <hi>Alſatia</hi> &amp; <hi>Sweden,</hi> Troops of factious perſons gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together, liberty is every where pretended, and all reverence and obedience due to Princes contemned, yea, altogether caſt off.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the progreſſe or increaſe of the Anabaptiſts.</head>
               <p>WHen Sathan had by this meanes indeavoured not onely to make Schiſmes in the reviving Church, and to caſt duſt in her face; but likewiſe to render the reformation of the Temple of the Lord odious to the powers of the world; as if thereby the juſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thourity of Princes over their ſubjects was abrogated; and the new preaching of the Goſpell, led onely to faction and ſedition; it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be expreſſed into how much hatred the moſt holy worke of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation was brought, with thoſe men which were ſtill addicted to their former ſuperſtition; For theſe tumults were not onely imputed to their true Authours, a few leaders of factious perſons; but like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe began to be layd to the charge of the Goſpell it ſelfe, and all the Teachers thereof. And that ſo much the more, becauſe theſe new Patriarkes of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> had afore-time beene familiar with
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113900:4"/>thoſe, whoſe ſervice the Lord had uſed in the Reformation of his houſe; and for that they boaſted, <hi>Luther</hi> was of the ſame minde with them. Hereunto adde, that the multitude ſtirred up by them, would ſeeme that they minded to ſticke to the Goſpell, and cleave to the Scripture onely: and would maintaine the liberty of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences by the ſword. But thoſe worthies, which had given ſufficient proofe to the Church, of their fidelity and integrity in repairing the Temple of God; that they might wipe off the blot which was caſt aſwell upon themſelves, as the Goſpell; they thought fit by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, to defend both their owne, and the cauſe of the Church of God; which amongſt the reſt, was ſtoutly performed by <hi>Luther, Melanch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Zuinglius, Bullinger, Menius, Regius</hi> and others, who ſharpely inveighed againſt ſedition, and ſeditious perſons; admoniſhing rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious ſubjects out of the word of God, of their duties towards the higher powers: reproving thoſe turbulent Preachers, and exhorting all to quietneſſe, and due reverence towards Princes: and left nothing undone, which they thought might ſerve to abate the violence of thoſe men, which with inraged mindes runne headlong unto all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſſe and miſchiefe. Chiefly <hi>Luther,</hi> being more vehement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, contented not himſelfe with exhortatory writings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but likewiſe ſet forth ſharpe Invectives againſt the unruly: and by a ſpeciall Booke publiſhed againſt thoſe Countrey Robbers and Murtherers, himſelfe denounced warre againſt them; exhorting Princes by force of Armes, to reſtraine the courſe of theſe Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and compell them to be quiet, which would not be perſwaded to it.</p>
               <p>Theſe new Doctors, <hi>Muntzer</hi> and his confederates, being rather made fiercer then milder by theſe admonitions, turmoyle ſtill more and more, crying out, that <hi>Luther</hi> and thoſe of his party, ſavoured nothing but the fleſh: vaunting indeed, that they have cut off ſome of the leaves of Antichriſt; but the tree and the rootes remained ſtill untouched; which muſt alſo be cut downe, and which cut downe they would. And ſeeing they could finde nothing in the written word of God, to defend their errours, and the tumults which they raiſed, they flye to new devices, to maintaine themſelves and their madneſſe, by boaſting of revelations, inſpirations; and alwayes inculcate to the inconſiderate multitude inclined unto them, <hi>that man muſt live by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word which proceedeth out of the mouth of God,</hi> and therefore muſt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113900:5"/>not ſeeke to be wiſe onely out of books and writings, but endeavour according to the preſcript of the Apoſtle, <hi>that they might all Prophecy.</hi> Hereupon every Fiſh monger begins to boaſt of the Spirit, feign re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations after the example of <hi>Storch</hi> and <hi>Muntzer,</hi> to counterfeit inſpirations: the Pulpit is open to every Cobler or Tinker; and what goodly dotage ſoever the method of deceit had dictated to any, without and contrary to the written word, was thruſt upon men for the word of God; ſcoffed at the publique Sermons of the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, inveighed againſt the Lutherane faith, as being void of good workes: ſome of their doctrines and myſteries they would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale, except to thoſe, who gave themſelves to miniſter about their holy things; others like the <hi>cuttell fiſh,</hi> they caſt their blackneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, that they might not be thorowly diſcerned; by ſtrange arts, lurked in Houſes and Families, gathering their conventicles in ſecret corners: profeſſe that they were ſent chiefly to the needy, and thoſe of meane condition; and by all kinde of craft and ſubtilty, ſeek to poſſeſſe and bewitch the mindes of credulous men.</p>
               <p>Having once opened a wide gate to errour, by enthuſiaſmes; all monſtrous opinions whatſoever, began to be obtruded upon ſimple people, and thoſe who were itching after novelties: and turbulent wits are ſtirred up, to introduce a new ſtate of things both in Church and Common-wealth, into the Chriſtian world. And that no regard either of conſcience, or fidelity ſworne to Princes, might be an hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to them; they began to publiſh, <hi>That Oaths in the time of the new Teſtament, were unlawfull; and therefore whether already taken, or to be taken, were altogether void and of none effect.</hi> Theſe foundations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once layd, the common people are over all, as it were ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, by factious Sermons, conſpirations made, and ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons armed againſt their Princes; and flouriſhing provinces waſted with miſerable civill warre, and ſtained with much bloud.</p>
               <p>The chiefe Trumpet, and kindler of theſe uproares, was this <hi>Muntzer,</hi> who having gotten himſelfe authority amongſt the heed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe common people, began openly to proclaime, <hi>That he was raiſed up by the command of God, for the puniſhment of wicked Princes, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering of Politicke Government.</hi> For this cauſe, being by <hi>Frederick E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of Saxony,</hi> driven out of that Country, and wandering here and there through <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Helvetia,</hi> he ſowed the ſeeds of ſedition every where; and at length, being returned to <hi>Mulhayſen,</hi> a famous
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113900:5"/>Towne in <hi>Thuringia,</hi> he came to that height of preſumption, that by the helpe of factious perſons, and ſuch as were addited unto him, he put off the Magiſtrates, and filled the Court with his Sectaries; yea, challenged to himſelfe the cognizance of all, both Eccleſiaſticall and Civill matters; ſpreading this Doctrine, <hi>that judgements under the new Teſtament ought to be framed and adminiſtred onely out of the word of God.</hi> And that the hearts of the common people might be the more faſtly knit unto him, who have commonly but ſmall revenues; he would not onely that all Monaſteries ſhould be prey and ſpoyle unto them, but likewiſe <hi>commanded that all things ſhould be in common,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the example of the Primitive Church: and thoſe of the richer ſort, he either by Arguments perſwaded to aſcent, or by force, and feare of worſe compelled them thereunto. When nothing in ſhew more favourable then this, could come to the eares of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people; who had either beene burdened with taxes, or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time oppreſſed by the more hard government of their Superious; or which were in want and penury: and <hi>Muntzer</hi> by his ſeditious let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſent abroad every where by his Meſſengers, publiſhed this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; and withall preached all manner of liberty: grievous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions followed in many provinces, eſpecially in <hi>Sweden, Thuringia,</hi> and <hi>Franconica,</hi> where the clowniſh multitude ariſing in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers betake themſelves to Armes; contemne the commands and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of the Magiſtrate; pull downe all Caſtles, and fortreſſes, as the fetters put upon their liberty. <hi>Muntzer</hi> yet ſets the mindes of thoſe men more on fire, who were already more then enough enraged: cals the Minets out of the Mines of <hi>Mansfield</hi> unto prey and tumult, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth to all, <hi>That he is the ſervant of God, ordained by Heaven, to cut off the ungodly; and that God had committed unto him the ſword of Gideon?</hi> ordinarily uſing this ſubſcription in his letters. <hi>Thomas Muntzer the ſervant of God againſt the ungodly;</hi> as alſo, <hi>Thomas Muntzer with the ſword of Gideon.</hi> And yet is the minde of this mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,<note place="margin">The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts enter the field with an Army.</note> more and more inflamed, by one <hi>Henry Pfeiffer,</hi> who of a Monke, become a brawler, counterfeiting a viſion from Heaven, gathers forces of mutinous perſons, and brings forth his Troopes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the field. The Princes of <hi>Saxony, Brunſwicke</hi> and <hi>Heſſen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Princes of <hi>Germany</hi> make warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</note> with the <hi>Count of Mansfield,</hi> being by the Rebels conſtrained to Armes, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare likewiſe an Army: and after many admonitions ſpent to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, they ſet upon theſe bands of husbandmen rather then Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113900:6"/>which were ſet downe on the hill neer the Towne of <hi>Franken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hayſen;</hi> whom (quaking before the fight began, and in vaine exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Muntzers</hi> trembling voice to courage and conſtancy) they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow and put to flight; ſtorme the Towne of <hi>Frankenhayſen:</hi> and <hi>Muntzer</hi> who had fled thither, and fained a ſickneſſe, (as being pined away with long faintneſſe) being through the ſingular provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, diſcovered by the ſervant of a Noble-man, by certain letters hid in his cloakbagge, neer the bed where he lay, was plucked out of his hole,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Pfeiffer</hi> taken and hanged neer <hi>Mulhayſen.</hi>
                  </note> and together with his conſort <hi>Pfeiffer</hi> committed to ſafe cuſtody: where having by the Racke and Tortures, compeld him to declare the names of his complices; he almoſt deſperate (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Pfeiffer,</hi> who was taken neer <hi>Iſenacke</hi>) paid for his wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the death of ſo many thouſands; being cut off with the ſword of vengeance, by the hand of the hangman, neer <hi>Mulhayſen,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1525. Otherwhere alſo in <hi>Sweden, Thurin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia, Alſatia, Franconia, Bavaria, Auſtria and Stiria,</hi> were the Princes Armes victorious; the routed Troops of the Ruſticks, are ſcattered in every place; the Cities poſſeſſed by theſe factious men, are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther taken by force, or conſtrained to deliver up, and by the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a few, many are reſtrayned, all terrified, this ſpreading evill ſtayed; and the former peace and tranquillity again reſtored to thoſe Provinces.</p>
               <p>Theſe frantick and ſeditious men, being ſubdued by force in <hi>upper-Germany;</hi> and the ſpring of rebellion, with the loſſe of much bloud, at laſt drawn dry: this evill grew freſh again in <hi>Helvetia;</hi> and thoſe ſeeds of <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> which had been ſowne by <hi>Muntzer</hi> traviling through theſe parts; and received with open eares and mindes by ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Word; began both in publique and private aſſemblies to be preached unto the common people. Of which Preachers the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal men were <hi>Foelix Mantzy</hi> &amp; <hi>Conradius Grebelius</hi> of <hi>Zurich,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the firſt had ſtrived in vaine to come to the profeſſion of the <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew,</hi> and the other of the <hi>Greeke</hi> tongue, and <hi>Balthazer Hubmeier,</hi> Paſtor of the Towne of <hi>Waldſhut:</hi> who when he had not onely by word, but alſo by publiſhing a booke of <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> troubled the conſciences of a great many; <hi>Huldricus Zuniglius,</hi> that valiant Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of the truth, ſet forth a writing, and confuted the turbulent fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. And at <hi>Zurich,</hi> in a ſolemne diſputation with the two former, for three dayes together, in the month of <hi>November,</hi> publiquely in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113900:6"/>the Court (after two others had with them, in the month of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> and <hi>March</hi>) in the yeare of our Lord 1525.) ſolidly confuted their Arguments, or rather cavillations againſt Childrens Baptiſme, (which they contended was firſt inſtituted by <hi>Pope Nicholas</hi>) in full demonſtration of the ſpirit, and of power. <hi>Anabaptiſme</hi> being tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over in this diſputation, by the helpe of <hi>Zuriglius, Leo Juda,</hi> and <hi>Caſper Megander,</hi> and the truth laid open to the light; the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate of <hi>Zurich</hi> by a publique edict eſtabliſheth Childrens Baptiſm, and command the <hi>Anabaptiſts teachers to be ſilent and quiet.</hi> Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as yet theſe troubles of the State would not ceaſe, but that in private meetings, they had not onely perſwaded <hi>Anabaptiſme</hi> againe to many of the Citizens, but alſo divers of them, who had addicted themſelves to theſe new Patriarks, were rebaptized.</p>
               <p>To this thing lend their aſſiſtance, <hi>Gulielmus Raubli, Panicellus Brotlcin, George Blaurock, John Denck,</hi> and <hi>Andrew Stultzy;</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others <hi>Hubmeir:</hi> who having at firſt taught the Goſpell at <hi>Waldſhut,</hi> a Towne in the confines of <hi>Helvetia;</hi> and afterwards tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and ſo (having ſet the Citizens together by the eares, for this diverſity of opinions) made the City again liable to the Armes of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the Idolatry of the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> had fled to <hi>Zurich,</hi> and there lurked privily amongſt his diſciples, untill being apprehended by the Senate, and commanded to anſwer to what ſhould be laid to his charge; he was by <hi>Zuniglius</hi> out of the word of God, proved guilty of divers errors. But he of his owne accord, promiſing to make a publique recantation, when he aſcended the Pulpit, againe preached his errors unto the people. Being reprehended for this thing, and confeſſing that it was inſpired into him by Satan, at laſt after many promiſes,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hubmeier</hi> bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich.</hi>
                  </note> and forſwearing the Tenets of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> he was baniſhed the City. But as men are apt to ſtrive for what is forbidden them, and deſire the more that which is denyed them; ſo could not all this reſtraine the rude multitude, but that they ſecretly favoured the opinions of theſe fanaticke men, which were with much art and eloquence commended unto them by the Teachers of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> moving them, beſides the novelty of the doctrine, a certaine vaine affection of pitty towards theſe new E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangeliſts; who ſeemed rather miſerable then evill, and more prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall of their quietneſſe then faith; reputing their ſtubbornneſſe for true conſtancy. Inſomuch as the Senate of <hi>Zurich</hi> was at laſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113900:7"/>to indeavour to prevent the ſame, by a ſevere edict in the yeare of our Lord 1530.<note place="margin">Capitall puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment decreed againſt the Teachers of the Anabaptiſts, and fines layed upon thoſe that receive them.</note> decreeing capitall puniſhment upon the Teachers of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and heavy fines upon any that ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them. The opinion of <hi>Hubmeier</hi> amongſt others, was, <hi>that the ſpirit of Adam did not conſent to ſinne, and therefore remained perfect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſinne committed; neither did it looſe its liberty, but the fleſh onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The field of <hi>Bazill</hi> likewiſe being ſowne with theſe unhappy tares, there alſo did the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> make ſtirres and uproares: with whom <hi>O Ecolanpadius</hi> a grave Divine encountring in the City of <hi>Bazill,</hi> in the yeares 1525, 1527, 1529. about the articles of <hi>Childrens Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, Rebaptiſing, the Civill Magiſtrate,</hi> and <hi>Oaths;</hi> gave abundant ſatisfaction to the cauſe, though not to the obſtinate agents thereof; ſo that by the authority of the moſt prudent Magiſtrate, the zealous aſſertor of Gods glory, uſed in ſuppreſſing thoſe Sectaries; both the peace and purity of the Church of <hi>Bazill</hi> was preſerved.</p>
               <p>The peace of the Common-Wealth of <hi>Berne</hi> alſo, was not a little troubled by thoſe men; eſpecially by <hi>Ludovicus Hetſer, Joannes Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer,</hi> and <hi>Joannes Seckler;</hi> where the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> being admitted to a publique diſputation <hi>Anno</hi> 1528. their errors were manifeſted, and their ring-leaders confuted by <hi>Bertholdus Hallerus,</hi> and <hi>Francis Kol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> Miniſters of the word of God. But when notwithſtanding the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> muttered in corners, that there was as yet no ſatisfaction given them, that the truth might openly triumph over error, a ſolemn diſputation was againe appointed, by the honourable Magiſtrate of <hi>Berne,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>A</hi> diſputation at <hi>Zoſing</hi> with the Anabaptiſts nine daies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</note> at <hi>Zoſing</hi> in <hi>Argovia</hi> within the Territory of <hi>Berne,</hi> in the month of <hi>July, Anno Dom.</hi> 1532. which being accordingly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, between the Miniſters of the Church of <hi>Berne,</hi> and the Teachers of the <hi>Anabaptists;</hi> and continued for nine dayes together; and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king by publique notaries, and publiſhed to the world; was of great moment for the confirmation of many mens mindes in the truth, and recalling others from their errors. And when about the yeare 1579. the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> began againe to raiſe new ſtirs in the country of <hi>Bern;</hi> by the vigilancy of the Magiſtrates and ſevere edicts, the Sectaries were curbed and the growing evill repreſſed.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Sengall</hi> likewiſe a Town of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> confederated with the neighbouring villages, no ſmall adoe was made by <hi>Conradus Grebelius</hi> and his diſciples; and by all ſtratagems, ſecret ſuggeſtions, publique ſerrnons, writings, and all manner of allurements indeavored, that
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113900:7"/>this famous City might be made a <hi>Pella,</hi> and receptacle to theſe kinde of men; But through Gods ſpeciall mercy, by the writings of <hi>Zunig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">They are caſt out of the City <hi>Sengall.</hi>
                  </note> the zeale of <hi>Ioachimus Vadianus,</hi> and the prudence of the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, that was prevented, and theſe troubleſome fellows caſt out of the City. Not a little conduced, to render the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> hatefull un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all good men in this City; the horrible fact of <hi>Thomas Schucker,</hi> diſciple of <hi>Melchior Rinckius</hi> that Champion of the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> For hee on a time, when a great throng of this kind of people were gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed together, counterfeiting a rapture and revelation from heaven; commanded his brother <hi>Leonard Shucker</hi> to kneel down on his knees, and aske for a Sword. Being demanded by his father, mother,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>The Schucker</hi> an Anabaptiſt cuts off his brothers head in a rapture.</note> and others that ſtood by, what he meant by this poſture; anſwered, that they ſhould be of good cheare, for he would doe nothing but what was revealed him from heaven. The minds of all being attent to this new ſpectacle, the mad prophet with his drawne ſword, cuts off his brothers head from his body, at one blow, and tumbles it to the earth; ſtriking exceeding terrour into all the beholders, and drawing from his parents great grief of heart, and many groanes.<note place="margin">He is executed for it.</note> Being apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Magiſtrate for this cruell murder; he received the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment due to his wickedneſſe; nevertheleſſe ſhewing no ſigne at all of any remorſe for his crime, but profeſſing on the Scaffold that this was the will of God, revealed unto him from heaven. This tragicall chance hapned in <hi>Sengall, An. Dom.</hi> 1527. which not a little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the mind of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and ſtirred him up againſt theſe furious prophets and their ſonnes, and cauſed him to publiſh Seven Edicts againſt the abode of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> in their City or do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions. The departure of thoſe men gave indeed reſt and quiet to the City of <hi>Sengall,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Seven Edicts againſt the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in thoſe parts.</note> but bred new turmoyles in the neighbour Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of <hi>Abbas-Cellonſis;</hi> thoſe reſtleſſe perſons ever wandring here and there, to make innovations, and trouble the worke of reformation there began.</p>
               <p>Satan being throwne out of this Theatre likewiſe, would needs erect himſelfe another, in many of the moſt flouriſhing Cities of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many:</hi> and at <hi>Straesbourg</hi> by <hi>Hoſman,</hi> at <hi>Wormes</hi> by <hi>Cantius,</hi> at <hi>Auſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> by one <hi>Iames a Tauner;</hi> at <hi>Vlms</hi> by <hi>Kleiber,</hi> and at other places by others, began to ſpread and ſow abroad the doctrine of <hi>Azabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme:</hi> whoſe attempts were withſtood, both by the Magiſtrates and other of Gods faithfull ſervants, the turbulent men ſuppreſſed, their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113900:8"/>peſtilent doctrine in publique meetings confuted, and by ſolemn E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts reſtrained: although alwayes under deceitfull aſhes lurked the fire kindled by theſe raging Doctors, which ever and anon brake out in divers places.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Anabaptists</hi> being driven out of <hi>Helvetia</hi> and <hi>Vpper Germany,</hi> many of them departed into <hi>Moravia;</hi> and there joyned themſelves to factious men of this ſort, who were itching after novelties. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by divers ſleights gathered them many Congregations there, and ſent forth many of their meſſengers into the neighbour Provinces and Kingdomes; the ſame plague brake out in <hi>Bohemia, Poland, Hungary, Austria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Anabaptiſts beheaded.</note> and <hi>Sileſia;</hi> which when ſeditions and diſturbances every where followed, ſome of them being caught, paid for their unrulineſſe with the loſſe of their heads; amongſt whom was <hi>Balthazar Hubmeier,</hi> who for having made tumults in <hi>Moravia,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hubmeier</hi> an Anabaptiſt for raiſing tumults was burnt at <hi>Vienna</hi>
                  </note> was brought to <hi>Vienna,</hi> and there burnt. This being by the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> eſteemed martyrdome, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kindled, then quenched or aſſwaged the heat of their fury: nor did they ceaſe any whit the more for that, to uſe all maner of devices, which either zeal without knowledge could ſuggeſt unto ſimple men, or which the cunning jugling of their Ring-leaders could invent, for the eſtabliſhing and increaſing of their Sect: of which the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the forementioned doctrine of communion of goods, was not the leaſt; and which was with ready minds and Ears received of the rude rabble, who had ſmall means of their own, and all their hopes on other mens. But this a little ſlackned the progreſſe of the Sectaries, that (as the wits of men are never at reſt) the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Moravia</hi> began to divide into divers parts, of one Sect becomming two, the one of the <hi>Gabrieliſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In <hi>Moravia</hi> the Anabap. divide into ſeverall Sects.</note> the other of the <hi>Hutterians,</hi> ſo named from two of their Ring-leaders, <hi>Iacobus Huttering,</hi> and <hi>Gabriel Schevering,</hi> who were the firſt that lighted ahe Candle to theſe Sectaries in <hi>Moravia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As <hi>Vpper Germany</hi> was thus ſubject to the uproares of the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts,</hi> ſo neither was <hi>Low Germany</hi> free from this ſpirit of giddines; but the flouriſhing Provinces of <hi>Weſtphalia, Friezland,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> were grievouſly vexed with theſe new apoſtles; by whom, vanting nothing but the word of God, and revelations from heaven, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuating themſelves by a certaine outward civility of life, a very great multitude of people were corrupted, and infected with this leaven of <hi>Anabaptiſme:</hi> but chiefly <hi>Munſter</hi> a famous <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> was beſet with theſe new prophets; which they did as it were by degrees.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113900:8"/>For when at firſt by the labour of <hi>Bernard Rotmannus</hi> the doctrine of the Goſpell began to bee taught in this City, a great multitude of people adjoyned themſelves thereunto, the Papiſts in vaine ſtorming thereat. <hi>Rotmannus</hi> ſends to <hi>Marpurg,</hi> deſiring to have ſome Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſent from thence unto his aſſiſtance; by whoſe helpe and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, the worke of reformation ſo happily began might bee more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced. There being ſent unto him <hi>Petrus Wirthemius</hi> and <hi>Godfrey Stralen, Rotmannus</hi> with his fellows provoke the Papiſts to a ſolemn diſputation, ſets downe their errours in writing, and promiſeth a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation of the ſame, out of the Word of God. But when the Popiſh Doctors confeſſed that they were unable to undergoe the encounter, and that they could not defend their doctrine by the Scripture, they were removed from the office of publique Teaching, and ſixe Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples occupied by the reformed. The <hi>Canonicks,</hi> and their followers, complaine to the Biſhop, of the injuſtice of thoſe of <hi>Munſter;</hi> he by letters commands that the new Preachers ſhould bee put out of Towne, and his owne reſtored againe. But the <hi>Biſhop</hi> having ſpent many threatnings to no purpoſe, and the number of Proteſtants growne greater then could bee contained in a little roome; by the mediation of the Illuſtrious <hi>Laudgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> the buſineſſe was compounded; the Proteſtant Preachers having certaine Temples al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed them; the Cathedrall being left to the <hi>Canonicks,</hi> the Biſhop enjoying his right; and they their ordinary revenues. When from that time forward every one had followed his own Religion quietly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>A</hi> Baker, and a Tailor, two Anabap. get in at <hi>Munſter</hi> and infect the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt doctrines.</note> for the ſpace of divers moneths; at length there come ſecretly to <hi>Munſter</hi> certaine of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1533. of whom the principall were <hi>Iohn Matthijz</hi> a Baker of <hi>Harlem,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Bocold</hi> a Taylor of <hi>Leyden;</hi> who being privily received by ſome of the Citizens, gather night meetings in Corners, teach a new Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, condemne childrens Baptiſme; and not onely learne their diſciples a new doctrine of Baptiſme; but make them to receive it againe; and urge community of Goods. When theſe new Doctors, eſpecially <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> had by a certaine alluring force of ſpeech, and fained ſhew of piety (having otherwiſe a perſon fit for a Prince,) crept into the minds of the credulous people,<note place="margin">Men in debt, and of low e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, and incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to miſchief ioyn unto them</note> in a ſhort ſpace the new ſect grew very numerous; ſeeing all thoſe joyned themſelves unto it, whom either their debts preſſed, or had but little means at home; yea all ſuch whoſe minds were inclined to miſchiefe and miſ-rule.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113900:9"/>To theſe were added a ſwarme of ſtrangers, called thither by the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> out of the neighbouring Provinces; upon whoſe comming the new prophets being more emboldned, they began to contend with the reformed Miniſters about childrens Baptiſme.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rotmannus</hi> and other miniſters go over to the Anabaptiſts.</note> 
                  <hi>Rotmannus</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſaile to follow the winde of popular applauſe, firſt faintly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelfe to the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> afterwards contrary to his pligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faith, yeelds them the victory, and openly goes over unto them; as likewiſe doe <hi>Herman Strapeda, Henricus Rullius, Godfrey Stralen,</hi> and more others. The City being divided into parties and factions; the Senate ordaines a publique diſputation concerning the doctrine. There encounter in the moneth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">After a diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part the City.</note> 1533. <hi>Rotmannus</hi> and other of the Sectaries; with <hi>Hermannus Buſchius, Ioannes Glandorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Petrus Worthemius, Ioannes Holtman,</hi> and their fellows. When here likewiſe the Truth triumphed over Errour; by order of the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were commanded to depart the City. They fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a departure, hide themſelves ſecretly in their holes; and being bold upon the favour of many of the Citizens, ceaſe not in their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate meetings to defend their cauſe, confirme and ſpread their new doctrine. Divers tumults ariſe in the City, grave perſons and thoſe that favoured the Orthodox Religion, either foreſeeing the enſuing miſchiefe, or overcome with feare, departed out of the City. From diſputations it came to fighting; and thoſe which before were forced to hide themſelves,<note place="margin">They riſe up in armes againſt the reformed. They not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, aſpire to the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their pleaſure.</note> now come forth in battell array againſt the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. At laſt peace and liberty of conſcience being eſtabliſhed on both ſides, all controverſies are laid aſide; but for a time onely. For neither did it ſeem enough to theſe giddy headed men, who delighted in nothing but ſtirs and novelties, to have obtained liberty to them and theirs, except they aſpire alſo, to all manner of licentiouſneſſe, to governe and diſpoſe of all things according to their owne pleaſure. The new prophets <hi>Iohn Matthijz,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden,</hi> counterfeit rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures and inſpirations, and by ſending forth horrible cries about the ſtreets and croſſe wayes, exhort all men to repentance; many wonders are noyſed amongſt the common people; from <hi>Oſnabrug, Weſell,</hi> and <hi>Warendorp,</hi> and the neighbouring Townes, were called hither all ſuch as were inſtructed in the myſteries of <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> under the glorious promiſe of receiving an hundred fold, for the goods that they left. Moſt of the Senators goe out of Towne,<note place="margin">They create new Magiſtrats</note> the reſt are put off, the face of the City quite altered; new Magiſtrates created by the prophets,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113900:9"/>and amongſt the reſt <hi>Bernard Knipperdolling,</hi> an old Innovator, ready of his hands, and as it were made of purpoſe for tumults. To whom Brethren were adjoyned, all men of the ſame order and diſpoſition. Over the Church aſſemblies were ſet, one <hi>Julius</hi> of <hi>Frieſland, Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus</hi> and others. The Monaſteries and Temples are ſpoiled; a huge deale of prey is gotten together, and uſed in common; yea, by a new ordinance of the Prophets, community of all goods is commanded upon paine of death;<note place="margin">They com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munity of all goods upon pain of death, they aboliſh Schooles and Church aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies.</note> all bookes except the Bible are caſt into the fire; Schooles aboliſhed; yea, and publique Church aſſemblies: the Prophets often redoubling, happy would that time be, when all ſhould be taught of God. And when the City was beſieged by the Biſhop, the Prophets prepare forces, raiſe fortifications, caſt the Bels into Engines of warre, and parting the worke amongſt the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; not onely delude them with vaine words, but tire them out with hard labour; and by cruelty confirme their authority towards the gaine-ſayers. <hi>John Matthiiz,</hi> raſhly falling out amongſt the thickeſt of the enemies, with a ſmall company, being cut off, and the Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens mindes much troubled thereat; <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> thinking it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned him to repaire this miſchance, tels them that his death with the manner thereof, was long ſince foretold him; and ſo he and <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mannus,</hi> raiſe them all up, in new hopes, and expectation of a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous deliverance from the ſiege; and repulſing the enemy, who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times aſſaulted the wals without ſucceſſe, gained credit to their praedictions. Then as being taken with an extaſy, and drunke for three dayes, at length proclaimes, that by the command of their heavenly Father, twelve (factious) men, muſt be ſet over this new Iſrael, reſerving to himſelfe as the Prophet of God, authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto all what was Gods pleaſure.<note place="margin">They eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh Polyga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my and rage againſt thoſe that oppoſe it, they practiſe tyranny.</note> To cover his owne adulteries and monſtrous luſts, hee eſtabliſheth Polygamy, rageth againſt thoſe that diſſented, and by the ſlaughters of a great many ſtrengthens his Tyranny; ſo that upon the pleaſure of this ungodly man, depended not onely the fortunes, but even the lives of every one of the Citizens. Whoſoever durſt but ſpeak a jeſt word of the Prophets, was accuſed of Treaſon, and made a Sacrafice to the luſt of theſe miſcreants; and all divine and humane right troden under foote. Yea, ſo farre proceeded the madneſſe of this villanous fellow,<note place="margin">John of Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſet upon a Kingly throne</note> that by the craft of a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith of Warendorp, ſuborned by him, who fained a revelation and inſpiration; and the blockiſhneſſe of the bewitched people; this
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113900:10"/>ſcum of the earth, was ſet upon a Kingly Throne, and exerciſed a ſtage-player like Kingdome, in an oppreſſed City, prepared himſelfe princely furniture and attendance, uſeth all manner of cruelty, with whordoms,<note place="margin">He diſtributeth principallities and dukedoms at his pleaſure to his followers</note> murders and unheard of Tyranny; diſtributed amongſt his followers, Principalities and Dukedomes at his pleaſure, and by his meſſengers publiſhed abroad the Kingdome of Sion, and every where ſtirred up the country people to mutiny and rebellion; yea, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted ſuch miſchiefes, as will ſcarce finde credit with poſterity; aſcribing to himſelfe this franticke title: <hi>Iohn</hi> King of new <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> King of righteouſneſſe over the whole world. Of which may be ſeene at large <hi>Ioannes Sleydan</hi> in the tenth booke of his Comen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries: <hi>Lambertus Hortenſius Manfortius,</hi> lib. <hi>de tumultibus Anabapt.</hi> and <hi>Ioannes Wigandus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Pomezania,</hi> in his volumne publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of <hi>Anabaptiſme.</hi> This Stage-play, or rather Tragedy endured ſo long, untill the City was brought to the utmoſt miſery; and (the Citizens too late acknowledging their owne vaine credulity and the madneſſe of their Prophets) was by a ſtratagem taken of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden, Knipperdolling</hi> and other of the principall being caught, after ſome fruitleſſe conferences, <hi>Anno</hi> 1536. had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them,<note place="margin">The Ring-lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts are puld in peeces with burning pinoers, and <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> hangd up in a Cage.</note> and <hi>Antony Corvinus</hi> and <hi>Ioannes Kymaeus,</hi> divines of <hi>Heſſen</hi> both of them; with other conſorts of their villany, received the moſt juſt reward of their wickedneſſe, being plucked in peeces with burning pincers, and diverſly tormented, as thoſe which had deſerved more then one kinde of death: and <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> at this day hanging up in a Cage, teacheth poſterity to learne righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not to deſpiſe the Deity.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding, neither with theſe horrible fruits of <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> nor yet with the calamity of <hi>Munſter,</hi> were the mindes of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> diſmayed, in divers Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> and though many of them proteſted that they diſliked the madneſſe of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Munſter,</hi> yet tis certain that their chiefeſt Teachers in divers Provinces, were ſuch as were ſent out from them; and <hi>Memo Simonz</hi> although hee diſapproved of many things in thoſe of <hi>Munster,</hi> nevertheleſſe acknowledged them for brethren though weake ones; and profeſſed that their calamity notwithſtanding, they might finde God mercifull unto them. And indeed, this <hi>Memo Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monz</hi> came out of the Schoole of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bbo Philipz:</hi> and he out of the Schoole of <hi>Bartholomew Compactor,</hi> whoſe Apoſtleſhip is referred
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113900:10"/>unto <hi>Iohn Matthiiz,</hi> that famous Prophet of thoſe of <hi>Munſter;</hi> by whom hee, <hi>Theodoricke Cuyper, Claeſvan Alcmaer,</hi> and others, were firſt ſent forth. But how much this factious ſpirit ſtormed in <hi>Frie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſland</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> what uproares hee raiſed, eſpecially at <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and here at <hi>Leyden,</hi> yea throughout all <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Frieſland,</hi> and what dangerous plots he contrived for the deſtruction of thoſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is at large declared by <hi>Lamberous Hortenſius</hi> in the booke before cited. And although theſe tumults alwayes fell on the heads of their Authours, and their madneſſe and erroneous doctrines, were both by the Magiſtrates and Miniſters of the word, every where reſiſted: not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſo deep roots have this kinde of men taken in theſe Provinces; and their counterfeit ſhew of much ſimplicity, ſincerity, humility and charity, and ſpeciall reverence towards the word of God, ſo bewitched the mindes, eſpecially of the common people, and doth ſtill bewitch them; that many which are no evill men, but zealous of godlineſſe, joyne unto their party; and turne the looſe life of many of thoſe which are of the reformed Churches, into a prejudice of their Doctrine. Yea, at this day their doctors, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and writings, partly doctrinall, partly defenſive, and partly confutatory, ſtand in the maintainance of their errors: So that it concerns us to indeavour by all meanes to hinder the ſame, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide by all diligent care for the regaining of thoſe ſoules unto God, who are either led away with this error, or bred up in the ſame; and for preſerving thoſe from contagion, whom this peſtilentiall ſtarre hath not yet infected.</p>
               <p>Now as the builders of ancient <hi>Babell,</hi> by the confuſion of their tongues, publiſhed their owne wickedneſſe, and deſerved puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo in like manner, God would not onely that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſhould be ſtricken with a fingular blindneſſe, but likewiſe that their tongues ſhould be divided: and by his moſt juſt judgement permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that theſe Sectaries ſhould not onely diſſent from one another,<note place="margin">The Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts divide in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeverall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and they excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate one the other.</note> and rend into divers parts, but alſo that they ſhould with ſpitefull hearts and pens like ſo many new Midianites fight one againſt ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and with mutuall execrations teare out their owne bowels. For not onely the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Moravia</hi> depart one from another, but likeweſe thoſe of the <hi>Low Countryes,</hi> divided amongſt themſelves, thunder one family againſt the others, and for frivolous matters ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate one another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:113900:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the divers Sects of the Anabaptiſts, and of the names by which they are called.</head>
               <p>TO ſearch out the names, governments, and tenets, of all the Sects into which this Kingdome is divided, and wherein they diſſent one from another, would be of an over-tedious enquiry, yea ſcarce poſſible to any, except tainted, yea nouriſhed up in their Religion: this indeed is confeſſed, that many ſorts of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> were num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred of old, and are at this day, which drew their names either from the Doctors whoſe opinions they chiefly followed; or from the kind of life which they profeſſed, or elſe from the places where they had their reſort.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt ranke,<note place="margin">As firſt, Munt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zerians.</note> ſome were called <hi>Muntzerians;</hi> who inrolling their names under this ſeditious Doctor, or rather Captaine, intangled themſelves with his ungodly doctrine and miſchievous pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes. Others are called <hi>Huttites</hi> from <hi>Iohn Hutt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Huttites.</note> who according to their maſters example, called themſelves <hi>the corporall Iſrael of God;</hi> vaunted viſions and inſpirations (but ruefull and tragicall) <hi>cryed out that all the Canaanites muſt be cut off with the ſword; that the day of Judgment was at hand, and the Angels Trumpet began to ſound.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon many of them began to waſte away their meanes, as being an unprofitable burden for the world to come; but who afterwards bidden to begin long hopes, perceived themſelves brought to extream poverty; and found all too late, that their owne vain credulity, and their maſters mad promiſes, had coſt them very deare. Others were named <hi>Auguſtinians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3. Auguſtinians</note> from one <hi>Auguſtine</hi> a <hi>Bohemian;</hi> who beſides many other opinions common to the reſt, affirmed <hi>that the ſoules of the faithfull enjoyed not the ſight of God, nor had heaven open unto them untill the day of Judgment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others were called <hi>Hoſmannians.</hi> from <hi>Melehior Hofman,</hi> a wily fellow,<note place="margin">4. Hoſmanni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> and furniſhed with popular eloquence; who began to be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous at <hi>Straesburgh,</hi> and drew away a great company of diſciples af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him. To this <hi>Patriark</hi> is uſually aſcribed the firſt planting of thoſe <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> who ſo multiplyed in <hi>Lower Germany.</hi> For comming to <hi>Emden,</hi> An. 1528. when he had there with much poliſhing and a ſmooth tongue which he was excellent at, thruſt off his counterfeited
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113900:11"/>wares, he got great confluence of ſuch people as itched after novelties, and mightily increaſed this new Sect; and this our new Evangeliſt purchaſed ſo much authority, that by his diſciples, he was judged to be <hi>Elias, which ſhall be ſent into the World before the day of Judgement.</hi> Returning to <hi>Straesburgh</hi> upon the prophecy of an old man of <hi>Friez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and there publickly profeſſing <hi>Anabaptiſme,</hi> he not a little trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Church in that City. Whereupon a Synod being called in the Month of <hi>Iune,</hi> An. 1532 hee was admitted to a publique diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation with the Miniſters of the Word, by whom the opinions and dreams of the frantick fellow were confuted. When as yet he would not be at quiet and the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> bragged that <hi>Straesburgh</hi> was new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> in which a new Kingdome of Chriſt was to be erected, and joyned <hi>Cornelius Polterman,</hi> as an <hi>Enoch</hi> to that <hi>Eliah,</hi> and began to make uproares;<note place="margin">Hofman taken by the magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned.</note> 
                  <hi>Hofman</hi> is taken by the Magiſtrate and clapt into pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Out of which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> boaſted hee ſhould come with 144000. ſealed ones, which ſhould ſmite the earth with a curſe, and break thorow all the bars which were ſet upon him. That their <hi>Elias</hi> and <hi>Enoch</hi> ſhould be the two olive trees, and the two candleſtickes which no man could hurt; and if any man ſhould attempt it, fire ſhould come out of their mouthes, and conſume their enemies. But when theſe ſonnes of the prophets, had in vaine expected the deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of their <hi>Elias</hi> at the time foretold by other of their prophets: <hi>Hofman</hi> fearing leaſt he ſhould loſe his credit, or his diſciples their confidence, began to write out of the priſon; that they muſt be ſtill for the ſpace of two years after the example of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Haggai: whoſe ondevours for reſtoring the Temple of God, were in like manner ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed untill God raiſed up the ſpirit of Cyrus.</hi> Continuing thus obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his errours, at laſt dying in the priſon, he deceived all the hopes of his followers. The principall tenets of <hi>Hofman</hi> were,<note place="margin">Hofmans opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> 
                  <hi>that the word did not take fleſh of the Virgin Mary; whoſe fleſh was infected with ſinne, and accurſed: That Chriſt had only one nature; That the means of attaining ſalvation was in our own power: and by our free will was either imbyaced or rojected: That childrens baptiſme was not of God, but rather of the enemy of God and man.</hi> To this ranke pertaine likewiſe the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brielites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. and 6. Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brielites, &amp; Hutterians. 7 The Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonites.</note> and <hi>Hutterians, Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Moravia,</hi> who tooke theſe names from their Teachers before mentioned. So were other of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> long ſince, and are at this day termed <hi>Mennonites</hi> from <hi>Menno Simonz,</hi> a famous apoſtle of the <hi>Anabaptiſts:</hi> who borne in a
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113900:12"/>Village of <hi>Frieſland</hi> neere <hi>Harlingen,</hi> came indeed out of Popery, but into the errours of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> over head and eares: not only imbracing divers hereſies concerning the humane nature of Chriſt, Childrens baptiſme, the office of the Magiſtrate, and other points of that nature, but likewiſe by word, conferences, and writing, ſowed the ſame abroad every where: and although in a ſolemne diſputation with <hi>Martin Muronius,</hi> An. 1554 he could not with all his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry either elude the force of the truth, nor avoid the ſame; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he perſiſted in ſpreading, and defending his errours, till, that in the yeare of our Lord 1559. between <hi>Lubecke,</hi> and <hi>Hamburg,</hi> (or as others will have it at <hi>Old ſlo</hi> An. 1561.) he ended his daies, aged more then 60. yeares. The unconſtancy and contradictions of this brain-ſick Doctor; both the writings of <hi>Menno</hi> declare, and the Orthodox Divines have enough and more then enough manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed From this <hi>Menno,</hi> many <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> are now commonly called <hi>Mennonites,</hi> although all of them do not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low his opinions. The <hi>Mennonites</hi> properly ſo called, are likewiſe gone into divers parts, and ſome of them are called old <hi>Mennonites,</hi> other <hi>new,</hi> or latter <hi>Mennonites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Amongſt thoſe <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> which received names from their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, are uſed to be reckoned by ſome;<note place="margin">8. Servetians. 9. Georgians. 10. Swhenck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feldians.</note> 
                  <hi>Servetians, Georgians,</hi> and <hi>Swhenck-feldians,</hi> becauſe <hi>they oppoſe childrens baptlſno;</hi> and <hi>hold baptizang again, Inſpirations,</hi> and many other erroneous opinions common with the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> The <hi>Servetians</hi> are ſo called from <hi>Michael Servetus</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who for his execrable and unheard of blaſphemies moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately belcht out againſt the ſacred Trinity, and the Sonne of God, and other hainous crimes; was not only by the procurement of <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> that moſt learned and pious Divine, (which of meer malice is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by ſome) but upon mature conſultation, and communicating the matter with the Common-wealths and Churches of <hi>Helvetia,</hi> burnt at <hi>Geneva;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Servetus burnt at Geneva.</note> pouring out his ungodly ſoule amidſt moſt horrible blaſphemies in the very fire: and was aſwell by the judgment of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts as Proteſtants held moſt worthy to periſh, in the revenging flames.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Georgians</hi> were ſo named from <hi>David George</hi> of <hi>Delph</hi> in theſe <hi>Netherland,</hi> a moſt notorious Impoſtor, and patron aſwell of moſt horrible blaſphemies, as abominable and unnaturall luſts: who came to that height of preſumption and impiety, that beſides divers
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113900:12"/>other opinions wherein he conſpired with the <hi>Anabaptiſts; He gave himſelfe out for the Chriſt of God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The opinion of David George.</note> 
                  <hi>preferd himſelf before the eternall Son of the Eternall God, applyed unto himſelf the prophecies ſpoken by the holy men of God concerning Chriſt;</hi> and was ſo audacious, <hi>as to exalt his wicked and franticke opinions, above Gods holy Word,</hi> a moſt odious fellow, yea, a monſter and ſhame of mankinde. Which blaſphemies, together with other dotages of his; he hath gathered into his Booke of won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull things; where he likewiſe teacheth, that <hi>the doctrine delivered in the Scripture is unperfect, yea, childiſh, and carnall, and delivered as it were in the infancy of the World.</hi> And although one would thinke that theſe blaſphemies could not be perſwaded to any in the World: yet tis not to be ſaid, how great a multitude of men this moſt vile wretch drew to his party, chiefly by two meanes.<note place="margin">How he brought his followers to imbrace his opinions.</note> 1. An outward ſhew of an holy life and ſeeming continuall, and ardent powring out prayers unto God. 2. By a wary and crafty way of ſcattering, and inſtilling his opinions into others; making himſelf way by little and little from one degree to another, and by ſtrange meanes creeping into the minds of credulous men, and procuring credit and authority to himſelf. Nor would he reveale thoſe his horrible myſteries, except to thoſe onely, whom he had made wholly his own, and that ſecretly alſo. By which wiles and with a certain comly and majeſtical frame of countenance, he inveigled the minds of innumerable, and by the powerfull work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of deceit, ſeduced abundance of people for many years, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all cozened his diſciples of their mony:<note place="margin">He cheated them of their moneys.</note> until at laſt fearing the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved puniſhment of his blaſphemies, ſeeing he was ſharply reproved by <hi>Menno Simonz,</hi> and <hi>Melchior Hofman,</hi> and other of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> forſaking his ancient name, and taking upon him the new name of <hi>John</hi> a <hi>Bruck,</hi> he thought it ſafeſt for him to depart to ſome other place, where he was neither known by name nor face. He chooſeth the noble <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity of <hi>Baſill,</hi> whither to transfer the ſeate of his affaires:<note place="margin">He changed his name and fled to Baſill.</note> and ſeeing perſecution was very hot againſt the reformed Churches in theſe Provinces of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> profeſſeth himſelfe of the number of thoſe exiles, which were forced to leave their Country for the cauſe of Chriſt; and ſo with his Family, and ſome of his Sectaries, was received of the pious Magiſtrate; who tooke pitty upon ſuch as were for Chriſts ſake, faine to go into baniſhment. There the crafty fellow a long while hid his venome, and plighting his faith to the Magiſtrate, frequenting the Church aſſemblies, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113900:13"/>by divers good offices winning the mindes of a great many; and by his homely habit, liberall table, honeſt attendance, and prudent and civill converſation, gaining the favour both of high and low: he lived both ſafely and gallantly; having gotten himſelfe, beſides a ſpacious dwelling in the City, an houſe of pleaſure likewiſe in the Country: till in the yeare of our Lord 1556. about the month of <hi>September,</hi> rather by the gnawing worme of Conſcience, and feare of imminent puniſhment,<note place="margin">Where he pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned away and dyed.</note> then with any great ſickneſſe he pined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; when he perceived that by certaine ſtrangers of the <hi>Low-Countryes,</hi> continually flowing to <hi>Bazill,</hi> his vizard began to be pluckt off, and the mindes of his Sectaries began likewiſe to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. But which is wonderfull notwithſtanding, it was three years after the death of the Impoſtor (who was honourably buried in <hi>Lawrence</hi> Church) ere the vaile was withdrawne, and the ſtory diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered. Then were the blaſphemies of the ungodly man brought before the Senate, his Sectaries called into the Court, queſtion had with them concerning the name, Country, life and doctrine of the deceaſed. The houſes and cabinets of <hi>David</hi> and all his followers ſearched; their letters and books gathered together, and every thing delivered into the hands of Divines and Lawyers, to diſcuſſe the ſame. The blaſphemies and cozenages of this deceiver being dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, by a ſolemne ordinance of the Magiſtrate, all his bookes and papers are burnt by the hand of the common hangman; the picture of the naughty man,<note place="margin">His books and papers burnt by the common hangman, and his Corps con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to aſhes.</note> after it had been carryed about the Streets, in the malefactors Cart, was caſt into the fire; his infamous corps, brought in his Coffing into the publique place of execution, and there conſumed to aſhes. Thoſe of the Sectaries, which had aforetime been familiar with the Impoſtor, that proteſted, they had, and did abhorre the blaſphemies of their Maſter, had their lives granted them of the Senate, by whoſe piety and wiſedome, the contagion of this hereſy was hindered from ſpreading any further; all wayes of ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it abroad being ſtopt up,<note place="margin">His diſciples forſweare his opinions.</note> and they forſwearing publiquely in the Church the communion and doctrine of this falſe Teacher are admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to partake of the holy things. The reſt which pertaines to this hiſtory, is performed by <hi>Ioannes Wygandus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Pomezania,</hi> and the authour of the Hiſtory of <hi>David George,</hi> lately here publiſhed by the reverend man <hi>Iacobus Revius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Swenckfeldians</hi> were ſo named of <hi>Caſpar</hi> a <hi>Swenckfeld</hi> of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113900:13"/>
                  <hi>Oſſiga,</hi> a Knight of <hi>Sileſia,</hi> deſcended of a noble family in the <hi>Dukedome of Lunenburgh,</hi> who profeſſed, that <hi>he was ordained by God for the teaching, and propagation of the true Orthodox Religion;</hi> and for his ſingular gravity, care to live civilly, and fervency in prayer, made the mindes of many inclined unto him; eſpecially <hi>Valentine Craut-Waldius</hi> and <hi>Sigiſmund Wernerus,</hi> Profeſſors hnd Paſtors of <hi>Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> whoſe aſſiſtance he uſed in ſpreading abroad his opinions. <hi>Schwenckfeld</hi> and his followers, are reckoned with the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> for many poſitions which they held, partly the ſame with the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> and partly allyed unto them. He taught amongſt other things,<note place="margin">Swenckfeld o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions.</note> 
                  <hi>that the humane nature of Chriſt was no creature, but deified fleſh, or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up of the Divinity;</hi> ſaid <hi>that thoſe which defended the contrary opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, were creaturiſts;</hi> that <hi>the Scripture was a dead letter, and thoſe who taught other wiſe were voculiſts and litter aliſts; that illuminations and revelations ought to be highly eſteemed.</hi> To theſe opinions may be added thoſe concerning. <hi>Childrens Baptiſme, the Civill Magiſtrate, Oaths, and calling of Miniſters,</hi> of which <hi>Schwenckfeld</hi> wrote 80 bookes in his owne Language. But being baniſhed by <hi>Frederick, Duke of Lunen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh,</hi> in the yeare of our Lord 1527.<note place="margin">He is baniſhed.</note> he travailed thorow moſt of the principall Provinces of <hi>Germany,</hi> and ſpread his doctrine at <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riberg, Auſburgh, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lms, Straeſburgh</hi> and other places, and by his fine tongue, and ſhew of ſingular holineſſe of life, gained the mindes chiefly of the Nobility, and ſo poſſeſſed them, that at this preſent in many places of <hi>Germany,</hi> and eſpecially in the noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, there ſticks a kinde of ſecret veneration to the memory of theſe opinions received from their forefathers. Hee dyes at length in <hi>Sweden, Ann.</hi> 1561. aged more then 70 years, being honoured with this commendation. <hi>That he wanted a wel governed head, but not a good heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From the divers kindes of life and profeſſions,<note place="margin">11. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicks, why ſo called.</note> likewiſe ſeverall Sects amongſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> received their names. For others were called <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> others ſeparate from the world, or meerly ſpirituall; others <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> others <hi>Silenciaries,</hi> others <hi>Euchites,</hi> others <hi>Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſts,</hi> others <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> others <hi>Libertines,</hi> others <hi>Hamaxari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Borborites, or dungwagons.</hi> The Apoſtolicke were ſo called, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they profeſſed to be imitators of the Apoſtles, left their Wives, Children, Vocations, and Handy-crafts, wandred about without ſhooes, ſcrip, or mony in their purſes, waſhed one anothers feet, (whence they were alſo termed <hi>feet-waſhers</hi>) and commanded that all things ſhould be in common.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:113900:14"/>
               <p>The ſeparate from the world or ſpirituall were ſo named,<note place="margin">12. The Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the world why ſo called.</note> for that they would in nothing faſhion themſelves like to the preſent world, but in their clothing, feeding, ſleeping, walking, affected, ſpeciall holineſſe and ſingularity; deteſted publique meetings, ſolemnities of weddings, feaſtings, muſicke, and ſuch other worldly delights; yea, by the order of their Sect, avoided all laughter themſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it in others.</p>
               <p>Thoſe were named <hi>Cathariſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">13. The Catha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſts, their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</note> which not onely affirmed that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants were without ſinne, but likewiſe that men growne of their Sect, might and ought to be ſuch, and contended that the Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted onely of ſuch.</p>
               <p>Thoſe were called <hi>Silenciaries,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">14. The Silen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciarians, their opinions.</note> which not onely thought that much talking muſt be avoided but alſo private diſputations about Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, nor was there any more uſe of publique preaching; <hi>for that the doore was ſhut, and the times evill, and the world unworthy to have the Goſpell preached unto it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Euchites</hi> were ſo named,<note place="margin">15. The Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chites, why ſo called.</note> becauſe they aſcribed all force of keeping away evill, and attaining good things unto prayer onely, and contended that we ought to give our ſelves to them alone, and not ſeeke meanes neceſſary unto this temporall life, but expect all things immediately from the hand of God.</p>
               <p>Thoſe amongſt the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> are named <hi>Adiaphoriſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">16. The Adia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phoriſts.</note> which reckoned <hi>Childrens Baptiſme, Oaths, adminiſtration of Civill Offices, cutward preaching of the Word, giving and receiving of the Sacraments, confesſion of Faith,</hi> and things of the like nature, to be things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, teaching <hi>that the Spirit ſupplyed the defect of outward things, and that no man need to hazard his life for the profeſſion of his faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> are thoſe,<note place="margin">17. Enthuſiaſts</note> which boaſted above the reſt, of <hi>divine inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, extaſies, and ſecret communication with God,</hi> obtruding their Propheſies for the word of God, and preferring them before the written Word: yea, contended, that that was to be judged by their dreams.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libertines</hi> thoſe are called,<note place="margin">18. Libertines.</note> who gloried that they were freed by Chriſt from all lawes, both Divine and Civill; and feared not to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, and by their practice to confirme <hi>communion of wives, and ſuch other uncleans doctrines.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others are called <hi>Hamaxarians,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">19. Hamaxari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, or Dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wagon.</note> 
                  <hi>Borborites, or dungwagon,</hi> becauſe they making a ſchiſme from the old <hi>Mennonites,</hi> by reaſon of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113900:14"/>ſeverity of excommunications, received all other which were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by the reſt of the Sects into their communion, and ſo ſcraped all manner of durt together. The Authours of this Sect were <hi>Henry Naeldeman,</hi> and <hi>George Heyns,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Authours of this Sect.</note> in the yeare of our Lord 1555. The former number was yet increaſed by three new Sects which aroſe up amongſt the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Flanders</hi> a few yeares ſince, which with ſeverall excommunications rage one againſt another.<note place="margin">They excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate one another, the cauſes thereof</note> The occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this new divorce was the ſubtilty of one <hi>Thomas Beenkens, Biſhop of the Anabaptiſts of Franener;</hi> who publiquely offering a certaine houſe to ſell, deceived the hopes of a friend of his, which had inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it for himſelfe; he being by the craft of a cunning chapman put off from the ſame. This ſale was approved by many of the <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> as lawfull and without fraud, and eſpecially by <hi>Jacob Petervan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Meulen Biſhop of the Anabaptiſts of Harlem;</hi> others diſapproved it, and not onely condemned the batgaine as deceitfull, but alſo thought that it deſerved excommunication. Upon this occaſion they depart one from another, and both ſides finde their followers. Theſe being thus together by the eares, comes in a third-ſort of middle-men or neuters, who indeed condemned the bargaine as fraudulent, but thought that the ſin was not ſo great as deſerved excommunication. In the meane time, theſe three Sects albeit they agree in the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall articles of faith, grievouſly excommunicated one another, and obſtinately denyed to joyne in mutuall communion.</p>
               <p>For the third ranke of <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> ſuch as were named from the places and countries of which they were, or in which they neſtled and found entertainment; they have been of old diſtributed, into <hi>Germanes, Helvetians, Moravians, Netherlanders.</hi> The <hi>Germanes</hi> again ſubdivided into <hi>Swedes, Franks, Saxons</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Munſter;</hi> The <hi>Netherlanders</hi> into <hi>Fries, Flemmings, Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Waterlanders;</hi> The <hi>Fries</hi> are divided into <hi>Elder</hi> and <hi>Latter:</hi> Yea, ſometimes they take their names from Cities; as thoſe of <hi>Antwerp, Embden, Franequer, Leeuwaerden, Zirckzee, &amp;c.</hi> To ſet forth particularly and curiouſly, wherein all theſe doe agree or diſagree were to no purpoſe, nor is it eaſy to be done, ſeeing nothing can be more fickle then theſe kinde of men are, and points of Divinity are turned up and downe by them like dice; they uſing likewiſe doubtfull and uncertain phraſes; and wrapping up their meaning with manifold obſcurities; as alſo for the ſlighteſt matters (eſpecially for the opinion and exerciſe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication)
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113900:15"/>dividing one from another, and making more parties.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being before-hand conſidered, it is now manifeſt by what names theſe Sectaries are called, and for what cauſe they are given them: and they are either generall or ſpeciall; The generall are, <hi>Anabaptiſts, Catabaptiſts, Enthuſiaſts, Fanaticks</hi> and <hi>Libertines.</hi> Tis evident alſo, that they are called <hi>Catabaptiſts,</hi> becauſe they inveigh againſt <hi>Childrens Babaptiſme,</hi> and will have it baniſhed out of the Church of God, as being not onely unprofitable, but altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull. <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> becauſe they will have thoſe <hi>Baptized</hi> againe, which were either <hi>Baptized</hi> in their tender yeares, or in their riper, if out of their aſſemblies; and doe actually performe it, in thoſe that come over to their Sects. It appeares likewiſe that they are called <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> for the <hi>Enthuſiaſms, raptures</hi> and other ſuch like things, which they give out for <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>divine inſpirations;</hi> and for which, they will not onely have place given to their owne dreames, either in expoſition of the Scripture, or determining points of faith, or in direction of the eſpeciall actions of a mans life, but (at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe divers of them) aſcribe thereunto uncontrollable authority; for which cauſe alſo the name of <hi>Fanaticks</hi> was given them. It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares alſo that many have the name of <hi>Libertines</hi> either from their Tenets onely, or elſe from their Tenets and practiſe both. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of <hi>Libertines</hi> amongſt the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> ſome might be called <hi>Doctrinall onely;</hi> other <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uruly, Factious,</hi> and <hi>Epicures;</hi> of whom <hi>ſome have riſen up againſt the State,</hi> ſome practiſed <hi>the uſe of Wives in common,</hi> and other ſuch like impure and carnall deeds. To theſe generall names may be added alſo the ſpeciall, taken either from their Teachers, manner of life and profeſſion, or places of habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: all which may be gathered out of what hath beene before ſpoken.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> Of the Erroneous opinions of the Anabaptiſts.</head>
               <p>NOw for the Erroneous opinions of the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> they are ſo many by reaſon of the many Sects into which they are divided, that their number can ſcarce be caſt up. And although they might be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113900:15"/>divided into thoſe which are common to the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> with other <hi>Hereticks</hi> either Ancient or Moderne, and thoſe which are peculiar to them only: notwithſtanding for better order ſake I thinke fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all and every of them, to certaine common places of Divinity. And I ſhall comprehend in this diviſion, not thoſe opinions alone, which all the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> or <hi>Catabaptiſts</hi> have anciently maintained, or which all of them doe maintaine at this day; but thoſe alſo which many of them, or at leaſt ſome of them, have anciently, or do at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent defend; that ſo the partition may be the more perfect, and that I may preſent the Reader with the whole body of the Errours, which they have hitherto erred, and as yet doe erre. Notwithſtanding I ſhall not touch the Errours of <hi>David George,</hi> or <hi>Michael Servetus,</hi> (from which the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> for the moſt part proteſt, they ever have been, and ſtill are free) as neither the idle dreams of <hi>Schwenck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feld.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I make two generall Claſſes, unto which all the Heterodox opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> may be referred: for they either concerne the ſacred rule of Holy Scripture, or elſe the doctrines of Faith and ordinances which are taught in the ſame.</p>
               <p>What concerne ſacred Canon, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre.<note place="margin">1. Errours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Canon of the Scriptures, by detracting from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 1. About the matter of the Holy Scripture. 2. About the Forme. About the matter they offend. §. 1. By detraction there-from: while they reject the writings of the Old Teſtament as delivered to the <hi>Jews</hi> on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to the Chriſtians, and as being unprofitable for them; and imagine that only the Books of the New Teſtament muſt be the rule of our Faith, and walking; neither will they have proofs of the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Faith brought out of the Old Teſtament, to be received; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept when they are not contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that thoſe two writings are in many things contrary one to another, or that the Old Teſtament is of leſſe authourity then the New. <hi>Colloq. Francothall,</hi> and <hi>Leovard.</hi> and <hi>Confeſs.</hi> of the <hi>Mennonites.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. 2. By addition thereunto.<note place="margin">2. By addition to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</note> 1. While ſome of them equall the Apocrypha Books, with the Canonicall Scripture, and thinke that points of Faith may be proved out of them likewiſe. So <hi>Menno Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monz</hi> ſometimes oppoſeth the Apocryphall books of the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to the Canonicall; and the <hi>Mennonites</hi> his Sectaries in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ground their Tenets upon the books of <hi>Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> and the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113900:16"/>wiſedome of <hi>Solomon.</hi> So <hi>Reineir Wybrandz</hi> in his Catechiſme pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed at <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> Anno. 1640. divides the Books of the Holy Scripture into thoſe of the Old and New Teſtament; and the Books of the Old, into Canonicall and Apocryphall; although in this point he is not very conſtant to himſelf, and others of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> ſeem here to be of the ſame mind with the Orthodox. 2. while they teach that not only the written Word of God is to be hearkned unto; but alſo revelations, enthuſiaſms. dreames, and the immediate voyce of God, and according to theſe, the government of the Church, and all our actions, yea even very raſh and perillous ones ought to be regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; as appears by the doctrine and practiſe of thoſe of <hi>Munſter,</hi> and the conference of <hi>Antony Corpinus,</hi> and <hi>Ioannes Kymaeus,</hi> Divines of <hi>Heſſen,</hi> with <hi>Iohn</hi> of <hi>Leyden</hi> at <hi>Beve<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ga,</hi> An. 1536. §. 3. By alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration thereof; while they contend that the doctrine of Faith deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Old and New Teſtament is divers in ſubſtance, oppoſe <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> one to another, and teach that Chriſt in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath propoſed a new doctrine of faith more perfect righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not only earthly and temporall promiſes as were under the Old Teſtament, but moreover eternall. <hi>Colloq. Emba.</hi> and <hi>Leovard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the forme of the Holy Scripture the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend two marmer of wayes.<note place="margin">3. About the forme of the holy Scripture.</note> 1. About the internall form, while they will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit only that ſenſe of the Holy Scripture for lawfull, which is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in ſo many letters and ſillables, and (at leaſt-wiſe ſome of them) will allow no place to conſequences, and inferring one thing out of another; which appears partly out of the conferences had with them, concerning the expoſition of the words, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 1.14. <hi>The Word was made fleſh;</hi> where they will have the words and letters urged preciſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; partly out of their complaints, yea, triumphing that Childrens baptiſme cannot be proved out of the Holy Scripture in expreſſe words. For the ſame reaſon <hi>Peter Ioannes Moyoerus</hi> will have the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or the ſame eſſence hiſſed out; in his conference with <hi>Daniel Radeus.</hi> 2. About the externall forme, while becauſe of their ignorance and unskilfulnes, they will have us adhere to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Tranſlations of the Scripture in our mother tongues; and not to compare them with the Originall; and contend that the Orthodox Teachers ought not to have recourſe thereunto. So in the conference of <hi>Embden,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> urged that, three perſons ſhould be proved them in expreſſe words, out of <hi>Luthers</hi> Tranſlation, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113900:16"/>the Name <hi>Jehovah</hi> was not found there, they would not be preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed therewith. 3. While they thruſt upon us, for ſound, the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of their owne Teachers, eſpecially of <hi>Nicholas Biſcer</hi> which is many waies corrupt; as by divers conferences had with them ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares.</p>
               <p>The Second kind of Errours ſpreadeth it ſelf very far abroad; to wit which they erre about thoſe doctrines of Faith and Ordinances,<note place="margin">2. Errors againſt the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Faith, and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces taught in the Scripture.</note> which are drawne out of the Holy Scriptures; which for better diſtinction ſake, we ſhall diſtribute into things to be beleeved, and things to be done; and theſe latter, either in a publique eſtate, or private life. Things to be beleeved we ſhall pare. 1. into thoſe things which they will have beleeved concerning God. 2. Thoſe which they will have beleeved concerning the Mediator between God and man. 3. Thoſe which they will have beleeved concerning man himſelfe; and that either in the ſtate of integrity, miſery, reſtauration, or his eſtate after this life. Things to be done we divide alſo, into thoſe which they thinke ought to be done and obſerved of the whole Church in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or of every member in particular; and thoſe either publique, as in the policy, the civill Magiſtrate, and in the Church, thoſe which diſpence the Ordinances: or private, as are the reſt of the faithfull.</p>
               <p>This generall Anatomy, containes under it almoſt innumerable heads; for as one errour begets another, and one abſurdity being granted many more follow, ſo hath the ſame hapned to the Sects of the <hi>Anabaptiſts.</hi> A whole Sea of Errours have flowne into the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church; and by one, a ſtep made unto another, ſince the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts</hi> would have place given to their Enthuſiaſmes and dreames; like as the ſame hapned in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> when they once had let out their ſtreames of unwritten Traditions. Although we would have obſerved, that there is great difference between the Sects of the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> which either have been of old, or are found at this day, and ſome of them erre more grievouſly and dangerouſly, others leſſe. Neither were of old, all the ſame opinions maintained by them all; nor are at this preſent; but ſome of their Tenets are defended by them all, ſome by many, ſome by certaine of them onely: wherefore we will not have all laid to the charge of every one of them; but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend only to ſhew, how farre the licentiouſneſſe of thoſe franticke men, which have given their names to this Sect hath proceeded, ſince
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113900:17"/>they have departed from the Church of God, and made Schiſmes and Diviſions</p>
               <p>About the firſt generall head, namely, the things which they will have believed concerning God;<note place="margin">1. Errours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout things to be beleeved concerning God, 1. againſt the name of God.</note> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend. 1. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the names of God.</hi> 2. concerning <hi>his nature.</hi> 3. <hi>concerning the perſons of the ſacred Trinity.</hi> 4. <hi>concerning the Eſſentiall properties of God.</hi> 5. concerning <hi>Gods decrees.</hi> About the names of <hi>God</hi> they erre. 1. By contemning the name <hi>Jehovah,</hi> which denotes the Divine Eſſence, and which <hi>God</hi> will have proper to himſelfe alone; ſuppoſing that it is not in the Scripture, becauſe tis not to be found in many of their Tranſlations. <hi>Colloq. Embd. &amp; Confeſs. of the Anabaptiſts.</hi> 2. While they teach, <hi>that the perſons of the Sacred Trinity are called by the name of God, rather for the dominion which they have, then for that they have the divine nature. Iacob Outerm,</hi> in Articles. 3. While they contend that the name: <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>i. e. of the ſame Eſſence,</hi> ought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploded, as being both ambiguous and without the Scripture. <hi>Idem.</hi> in the ſame place; <hi>and Confeſs. of the Anabaptiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>the nature of God,</hi> the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend. 1. Negative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly while <hi>they deny that the Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Againſt the nature of God.</note> 
                  <hi>Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt have one and the ſame Eſſence;</hi> and affirmatively, not only indefinitely teaching <hi>that there are divers,</hi> but definitely making three Eſſences. <hi>Jacob Outerm. in Artic. &amp; Apology; and Cornel. Cuyper in Apol.</hi> 2. While they di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh the Eſſences of the perſons by diſtance of place, teaching that at Chriſts Baptiſme the Eſſence of the Father was in Heaven, and the Eſſence of the Sonne on Earth excluſively. <hi>Jbidem.</hi> 3. While they reſtraine the unity attributed to God, to unity of Will, Conſent, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, Operation, and Dominion, like as two Kings are ſaid to bee one, which command the ſame things; and as the Diſciples of Chriſt and all the faithfull are ſaid to be one, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 17.21. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. <hi>Iacob Out. in Artic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the Perſons, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend. 1. While they hiſſe out the name Perſon,<note place="margin">3. Againſt the Perſons of the Godhead.</note> as fained and ambiguous. <hi>Confeſs.</hi> 2. While they maintaine that the Name of God is principally aſcribed to the Father alone, and that he is therefore called the only true God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17 3. <hi>Confeſs.</hi> 3. While ſome of them leave it doubtfull, whether the Sonne of God were begotten of the Father from Everlaſting, or that he is ſo called becauſe he was foreknowne from Eternall, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated unto us. Yea <hi>Iacob Outerman</hi> plainly affirmeth that Chriſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:113900:17"/>was called God by the Prophets, and is the Eternall Sonne of God no otherwiſe then becauſe he was foreknowne for a Mediatour for us before the beginning of the World. So <hi>Claes Claeſs. in ſimpl. prob.</hi> teacheth that it is not clearely declared in Gods Word; whether the Sonne of God before his Incarnation was another perſon then the Father. 4. While the ſame man, in the ſame place teacheth; that we are not commanded to inquire whether from Eternal unto the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation of Chriſt, there were alwayes Three Perſons, indiſtinct as touching their Eſſence or not. Nor ought we to enquire, whether the Holy Ghoſt be diſtinct from the Father or no. Likewiſe they ſay, that they divide not the Perſons, but confeſſe that the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt are indiſtinct; nor is it taught in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that there are Three diſtinct Perſons. <hi>Colloq. Francothat. and Embd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the eſſentiall properties of God, they erre. 1.<note place="margin">4. Againſt the eſſentiall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of God.</note> While they deny the eſſentiall infiniteneſſe, and omnipreſence of God; affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, that not the incomprehenſible Eſſence of God doth fill heaven and earth; but his divine power and gifts; and that the former is falſly avouched. <hi>Cuyper</hi> and <hi>Outerm. in their Apologies.</hi> Yea they ſay that <hi>the Sonne of man was not then eſſentially in heaven, when be ſpake to Nic<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>demus upon earth. Out.</hi> So likewiſe at the Baptiſme of Chriſt, the Father was in Heaven, not on Earth, the Sonne on Earth, not in Heaven; neither is the holy Ghoſt in all places. <hi>Outerm.</hi> in x. <hi>Articl.</hi> 2. While they deny the immutability of God; for that the Sonne of God (ſay they) was changed; the Word being changed into fleſh; that Chriſt in his Incarnation forſooke his divine life and glory, and left to be like unto the Father aſwell in eſſence as properties. <hi>Idem,</hi> and <hi>Twiſck. in Anſw.</hi> 3. While they deny the inviſibility of God: for <hi>Outerman</hi> teacheth that God the Father ſhall be evidently ſeen with the Sonne at the day of Judgement; So was the ſecond perſon ſeen when Chriſt was made man, and ſo men ſaw the glory of the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne of God. In like manner <hi>Cuyper</hi> teacheth that the Holy Ghoſt was ſeen; for that <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw not a Dove, but the Holy Ghoſt in the likeneſſe of a Dove. Touching the decrees of God, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend. §. 1. About the generall decree of Gods provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.<note place="margin">5. Againſt the generall decree of God.</note> 1. While they overthrow the largneſſe therof; denying that God hath determined concerning all things by an eternall decree; or that he doth direct all things; yea affirming that 'tis abſurd to ſay,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:113900:18"/>that God from Eternity ordained all Events which are to come to paſſe; or the manner and meanes by which they are to come to paſſe. <hi>Knuyt in Pref.</hi> to his prayer Book, and <hi>Outerm. in demonſtr.</hi> 2. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that Gods providence extends unto Evils, and the direction of them; for that ſo God ſhould be made the author of ſinne. <hi>Outeim. in demonſtr. Knuyt in Pref.</hi> prayer Book. §. 2. While they take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the firmneſſe and unchangableneſſe of Gods providence; teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the ſame decree is not ſo immutable but that men can reſiſt it, and hinder the execution thereof, yea that the contrary is abſurd, and againſt the nature of Laws, Rewards, and puniſhments; and that theſe laſt ſhould otherwiſe be unjuſt. <hi>Outerm. Knuyt ibid. and Claes Claeſs. in Epiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They offend alſo about the ſpeciall decree of Predeſtination: And that concerning Election.<note place="margin">6. Againſt the ſpeciall decree of Gods prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtination, as 1. in election.</note> §. 1. ſouching the moving cauſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. 1. While they deny the free Election of ſome particular perſons to life eternall. <hi>Confeſs.</hi> of the <hi>Mennonites;</hi> affirming that Election to life depends upon fore-ſight of faith and obedience, and finall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance in them both, to wit, that thoſe are Elected to life, whom God foreſaw from Eternity, would believe in Chriſt, and obey him, and continue in their faith and obedience unto the end. <hi>Confeſs. Menno. &amp; Outerm. in dem.</hi> §. 2. Touching the firmneſſe of the ſame; teaching that it is not ſuch, but may be changed according as man carries himſelfe; for when it is grounded upon a changeable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it cannot chuſe but be changeable. <hi>Idem. &amp; Iohn Ries in Confeſs.</hi> of faith.</p>
               <p>In like manner do the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre about the doctrine of repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation. §. 1.<note place="margin">2. In reproba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Touching the moving cauſe thereof. 1. Denying that God out of the moſt free pleaſure of his own will, purpoſed to leave ſome of falne mankind in their corruption. <hi>Ibid.</hi> 2. Teaching that reprobation is grounded upon fore-ſight of infidelity, impeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and obſtinacy in the ſame; and conſequently thoſe are reprobated of God, whom he fore-ſees will be unbelievers and impenitent, and perſiſt in their infidelity and impenitency. <hi>Ibid.</hi> §. 2. Touching the firmnes therof; while they feine the decree of reprobation to be changeable, aſwell as the decree of Election, as being conditionall, and by reaſon of the mutability of the condition, the decree to be ſuch likewiſe; ſo that the number of the Elect and reprobates may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed or diminiſhed. <hi>Ibidem.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:113900:18"/>
               <p>Touching the Mediatour between God and man, Incarnated, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre many wayes; whether we reſpect his Perſon, office,<note place="margin">7. Againſt the mediator-ſhip of Chriſt.</note> or twofold Eſtate. In the doctrine of the perſon of Chriſt they erre. §. 1. About the Originall of Chriſts fleſh. 1. While they deny that the Sonne of God was made fleſh by aſſumption of the humane nature; but that he was ſo made by converſion rather; ſo that the Word it ſelf was turned into fleſh. <hi>Iacob Out. in Articl.</hi> Yea that the Word was made fleſh, even as the water was made Wine in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> of <hi>Galilee. Anabaptiſts</hi> of <hi>Antwerp. Menno Simonz,</hi> in his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence with <hi>Mieron, &amp; confer. of Embden.</hi> 2. While they deny that the body of Chriſt took its beginning out of the ſubſtance of the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary, but either of the ſeed of God the Father, or of his ſubſtance, or of the Word of God, or out of ſome other unknowne matter. <hi>Menno Simonz againſt Mier, &amp; in Confeſs.</hi> 3. While they teach that 'tis no matter of faith to know from whence Chriſt drew the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of his fleſh; neither is the diſtinct knowledge thereof neceſſary. In exhortation of the Church. <hi>Iohn de Ries in confeſs.</hi> to the Senate of <hi>Rotterd.</hi> §. 2. Touching Chriſts humane nature it ſelf. 1. By de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that Chriſt was made like unto man in all things, ſinne only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted; and affirme that it is raſhneſſe to ſay Chriſt is a creature ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his humane nature, and inferior to God; yea that the fleſh of Chriſt is divine fleſh. <hi>Iacob Peterz vander. Menleus Inſtitut. and Math. Ievriaenz. Epiſt. Chriſt.</hi> 2. Denying that Chriſt had a true humane Soule like unto ours. <hi>Confer. of Embden.</hi> 3. Denying that there are two natures in Chriſt with their Eſſentiall properties. <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Menno againſt Mier. &amp; confer. Embden.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Likewiſe do they many wayes offend in the doctrine of Chriſts office. §. 1. Concerning his propheticall office. 1.<note place="margin">8. Againſt Chriſts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall office.</note> While they contend that the New Teſtament was not revealed by Chriſt himſelf, till after <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> then when he actually and publikely admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred his office. <hi>In def. &amp; Apolog. neceſs.</hi> 2. While (in the ſame place) they maintain; That the doctrine of Chriſt, before his Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ought not ſo much to be obſerved, as touching all parts of it as after his death; for that <hi>Peter</hi> then reſiſted evill: neither was he caſt out of the Church for denyall of Chriſt; but now it ought to bee otherwiſe. 3. While they will have the doctrine and Law of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> ſo taken away by Chriſt, as it doth not any more obliege us; for as thoſe under the Old Teſtament were governed by the Law, ſo are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:113900:19"/>Chriſtians to be by the preaching of the Goſpell. <hi>Cl. Boeckarts ſir. Confer. of Franckendale: and Iohn Pet. Vander. Meulen compar. Script.</hi> 4. While they contend that Chriſt hath reformed the Law of the Ten Commandements, and ordained a new and more perfect one. <hi>Colloq. Embd. &amp; Francod.</hi> &amp; <hi>Confeſs. Mennon.</hi> So (for example) do they teach concerning the Firſt Commandement, that in the Old Teſtament, God the Father was only called upon: and that Chriſt in the New Teſtament, firſt taught his diſciples to call on the Father in the name of the Son. <hi>Confeſs of faith.</hi> So will they that the Third Commandment is more perfect in the New Teſtament, then it was in the Old for that in the Old Teſtament oathes were permitted, and perjury only forbidden, but in the new Teſtament all maner of oathes are altogether forbidden. <hi>Apoll.</hi> So touching the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, they maintaine that in the New Teſtament, the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath, is by Chriſt made meerly ceremoniall, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Sabbath only neceſſary to Chriſtians <hi>Confeſs. of faith. &amp; Apol.</hi> Likewiſe the Sixth Commandement permitted revenge in the Old Teſtament; and the Seventh, divorces, and Polygamy; by reaſon of the imperfection of the precepts of the Old Teſtament; but under the New Teſtament theſe things are not permitted.<note place="margin">9. Againſt Chriſts Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly office,</note> 
                  <hi>Apolog.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the Prieſtly office of Chriſt, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> offend. 1. While they think it not enough to aſcribe to Chriſt as God, ſufferings and death, as the perſon which ſuffered and died: but make the divine nature, that in which he ſuffered and died: as if Chriſt did not ſuffer and dye according to a nature truly and meerly humane, but accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a divine nature as it were turned into an humane: ſo that they either deny Chriſt to have been true God, or elſe turne his paſſion in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſeeming one only, as did the <hi>Marcionites. Iacob Outerm. Anſw. and Apolog.</hi> For otherwiſe (ſay they) we cannot be ſaid to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed by the death of the Son of God, and God ſhould be deprived of the due honour we owe unto him for our ſalvation. <hi>Confeſs. Men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non.</hi> 2. While they deny that Chriſt felt in his Soule the wrath of God, and the paines of Hell. <hi>Confer. Embden.</hi> 3. While they contend that Chriſt hath reconciled all men whatſoever, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difference unto GOD the Father; making one object of the acquiſition of ſalvation, and another of the application, that more large, this more ſtrict.<note place="margin">10. Againſt Chriſts Kingly office.</note> 
                  <hi>Conference Franckend. confeſs. Mennon. Iacob Onterm. Claes Claeſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning Chriſts Kingly office they offend likewiſe. 1. While
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:113900:19"/>they dreame of a carnall Kingdome to be ſet up by Chriſt in the Earth before the day of judgment. <hi>Monaſt. Lib. de Myſt. Scrip. and Lib. Reſtit.</hi> 2. While they deny the Almighty power of Chriſt, whereby he conſtantly preſerves all that are his, in the ſalvation once purchaſed for them, and the means leading to the ſame. <hi>confeſ. Menn. Claes. Claeſs. Epiſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the twofold eſtate of Chriſt, they offend moreover. 1.<note place="margin">11. Aagainſt Chriſts two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold eſtate 1. Humilation. 2. Exaltation.</note> Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſtate of humiliation; by teaching that Chriſt in his exina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, or emptying out of himſelfe, did not hide his divine glory; but verily quit and forſake it. <hi>confeſ. Menn. Jacob. Out. Apol.</hi> 2. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the ſtate of exaltation. 1. By denying that Chriſt raiſed up himſelfe from the dead, but was raiſed onely by God the Father. <hi>Cuyp. in Apol.</hi> 2. By teaching. that Chriſt in his aſcenſion, did not againe manifeſt the glory of his divine nature, which he had before concealed, but thereby really and fully recover againe the divine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and likeneſſe with his Father, which he before had loſt, <hi>Confeſ. Menn. Jac. Out.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning man, and Gods fourfold diſpenſation about him; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered according to divers eſtates,<note place="margin">12. Againſt mans-fourfold eſtate. 1. Innocenſie.</note> the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> doe many wayes offend. §. 1. Touching the State of integrity. 1. While they deny the holineſſe of the firſt man, to wit that he was created of God, furniſhed with originall righteouſneſſe and holineſſe; but onely in ſuch a diſpoſition, in which he might attaine unto both by a holy life. <hi>Briefe Inform.</hi> 2. While they deny the immortality of the firſt man; and ſome of them hold, that he was neither created mortall nor im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall; others, that he was created mortall of himſelfe, and in his owne nature, yea, and ſhould certainly have dyed although hee had beene without ſinne, and that death muſt have beene neceſſary unto him, that he might be tranſlated into glory. <hi>Ant. and Corn. Jacobz againſt Pupp.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching mans deſtitute eſtate they are faulty. 1.<note place="margin">2. The ſtate of man.</note> By taking away originall ſinne, denying that all men are by the diſobedience of one, made ſinners, the children of wrath, and ſubject to death; Although ſome of them ſeem not abſolutely to deny it. <hi>Conf. Franck. conf. Menn. Joh. de Ries Confeſs.</hi> 2. While others of them plainly deny that there is in Infants, any inclination and proneneſſe to evill; yea, ſome of them teach, that they are created in the ſame eſtate which <hi>Adam</hi> was. Others confeſſe, that there is in children ſome inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:113900:20"/>to evill, but deny that it proceeds from any originall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; but that men are inticed to actuall ſinne, onely by the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Satan, and bad examples; as for the inclination it ſelfe to ſin, however it be ingrafted into nature; notwithſtanding is not to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compted ſinne, nor is of it ſelfe guilty of damnation, but onely actuall and voluntary ſinnes. <hi>Conf. Men. Brief Inform. Claes Claeſ. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſ.</hi> 3. While they attribute to our free will in the ſtate of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, leberty to good and evill, and ſufficient ſtrength to underſtand, will and performe that which is good, and conſequently power to convert our ſelves. <hi>Confer. Leonard.</hi> and <hi>Embd. Confeſs. Mennon. Jac. Out. Apol.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning mans reſtored eſtate they offend, 1. While they teach,<note place="margin">3. Reſtauration by Chriſt.</note> that all men whatſoever without exception, whether Jews or Gentiles, whether faithfull and thoſe that ſhall be ſaved; or unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers and thoſe which ſhall be damned, are altogether reconciled to God by the death of Chriſt, and reſtored into the ſtate of grace. <hi>Confer. of Franck. and Embd. and Confeſs. of Mennon.</hi> 2. While they deny that there was any difference between Jews and Gentiles in the Old Teſtament, except in the ceremonies of the Law, and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and bodily cleanneſſe and uncleanneſſe. <hi>Neceſs. Vpolog.</hi> 3. While they corrupt the benefit of juſtification, partly before going, partly in the act it ſelf, and partly concerning the object therof. Before going, foraſmuch as they aſcribe to man, as proceeding from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, preparations to juſtification, to wit, hearing the voice of the Sonne of God, deſire of, and beſeeching for grace, ſpirituall hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and thirſt; and foraſmuch as they teach that this working toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with God is neceſſary that a man may be made partaker of juſtification. <hi>Claes. Claeſs. Conf.</hi> In the act it ſelfe, while they teach that God juſtifies us by faith, as it is a good worke, and obedience performed to the commandements of Chriſt. <hi>Joh. Pet. Vander Menl. Inſtit. Chriſt. Claes. Claeſs. Confeſs.</hi> Concerning the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, they likewiſe corrupt the doctrine of juſtification, while they teach that all men whatſoever are juſtified by the righteouſneſſe and obedience of Chriſt. <hi>Jacob. Outerm. Colloq. Embd. Neceſs. Apol.</hi> 4. While they corrupt the benefit of Sanctification, partly before-going; teaching that God doth not worke regeneration in us with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out our co-operation. <hi>Apol. Fund. Jac. Outer. Demonſt.</hi> partly in the act it ſelfe, while they aſcribe perfection of holineſſe to us Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grims
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:113900:20"/>here in this life, inſomuch as we can be free from all ſinne whatſoever. <hi>Brief Informat.</hi> partly conſequently, while they teach that the grace of Sanctification may be caſt off, and wholy loſt by the children of God; and therefore thoſe who are truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſuch, doe ſometimes totally and finally fall away, and incurre everlaſting damnation; and that this is manifeſt by the exhortations to perſeverance, by the carefulneſſe which is required of the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, and by divers examples. <hi>Confeſs. Mennon. Conf. Cl. Claeſs.</hi> 5. While they erre about faith; partly touching its originall, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that God alone workes the ſame in us, without our working to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with him, but that faith is the worke aſwell of man as God. <hi>Jacob. Outer, demonſt. Cl. Claeſs. Confeſs.</hi> partly touching the act it ſelfe, while they deny that faith is a firme truſt of the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of our ſinnes by the grace of God, for the merit of Chriſt; but confound it with obedience to the commandements, teaching that faith conſiſts partly in eſchewing evill, partly in doing good, <hi>Joh. Pet. Vand. Moul. Pref. to his Chriſt. Inſtit. Treat. of the</hi> 7 <hi>Artie. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Menn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching mans eſtate after this life, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre. 1.<note place="margin">4. The ſtate of glory.</note> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the place of Souls, teaching that the ſouls of the children of God, looſed from their Bodies, are not received into Heaven, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the day of judgement; but are untill then held in unknowne receptacles, not expreſſed in the Scriptures. <hi>Confeſs. Menn. and Claes. Claeſs.</hi> 2. Concerning the ſtate of ſoules, teaching that the ſoules of Gods children, enjoy not the ſight of God, yea, ſleep with their bodyes untill the laſt day; or at leaſt-wiſe like thoſe that are aſleep, are deprived of all knowledge, both intellectuall and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive. 3. While they deny that the ſoules of the wicked preſently after death, are caſt into Hell, and there puniſhed, for their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe before the laſt day of judgement; yee ſay, that they cannot be puniſhed before. <hi>Colloq. Embd. Confeſs. Menn. and Claes. Claeſs.</hi> 4. While they doe not onely deny the reſurrection of the ſame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes which were buried, but contented likewiſe that they ſhall be turned into Spirits, and deny that the dead ſhall ariſe having feet, hands, fleſh and bones, becauſe fleſh and blond cannot inherit the Kingdome of God. <hi>Conference of Frackendale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> maintaine grievous errors about things to be beleeved,<note place="margin">Errors about things to be done.</note> ſo doe they not a little offend about ſuch things as are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:113900:21"/>to be done; whether we conſider the whole body of the Church in common, or its members in particular, and thoſe either publique as in the policy is the Magiſtrate, and in the Church are the Paſtors; or elſe private as are every one of the faithfull, which profeſſe the Chriſtian verity in the Church of God.</p>
               <p>What concerns the whole body of the Church in common,<note place="margin">1. Concerning the whole body of the Church.</note> the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> erre while they imagine that thoſe which are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, are to be kept out of the Church, ſuppoſing that the Church conſiſts of none but thoſe that are perfect, &amp; according to theſe ought to be judged of. <hi>Cl. Claeſs. Conf. Menn. Summ.</hi> 2. While they will indeed have the Sacraments adminiſtred by the Paſtors, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by Chriſtians: but withall, will have them taught that they are but onely naked ſignes of the paſſion of Chriſt and badges of Chriſtians; but not ſeales of our communion with Chriſt. <hi>Conf. Leeuward. Menno Simonz booke of the fundam. Theod. Phil.</hi> 3. While they deny that the Infants of the faithfull, ought to be admitted, or accounted for members of the Church. <hi>Confer. of Franck and Embd.</hi> 4. While they will not have Miniſters adminiſter Baptiſme to In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants; nor Infants brought unto them for that end; yea teach, that it is an abuſe of Baptiſme, and an abomination before God. <hi>Colloq. Francothal. Embd. and Leov. Menno Simonz de fundam. Theod. Phil in Enchirid.</hi> 5. While they teach that Baptiſme con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd upon Infants, is by the Paſtors, to be repeated againe: and by ſuch Baptized to be admitted, yea, earneſtly defired: and thoſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ought to be Baptized againe, which were Baptized in other Chriſtian Churches; ſo that they will have even thoſe of their own party rebaptized, if they go over from one Sect to another. <hi>Colloq. Embd. Menno Sim. in his Summary. Theod. Phil. in Enchir.</hi> 6. While they teach, that the Lords Supper was inſtituted for none but pure and perfect ones; nor to be adminiſtred to any others then ſuch, nor to be ſought for, but by ſuch. <hi>John Pet. Vand. Meul. Chriſt. Inſtit.</hi> 7. While they condemne publique prayers pronounced with a loud voice, and thinke that all the Pſalmes are not fit to be ſung in publike aſſemblies. <hi>Frans. Knuyt. Pref. Cl. Claeſs. Ep. demonſtr.</hi> 8. While they will have Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline exerciſed againſt offenders, by all the members of the Church promiſcuouſly, and that without either convenient admonition afore going, or conſideration of their repentance following. <hi>Coll. Embd. Leov. and Conf. Menn.</hi> 9. While
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:113900:21"/>they teach, that when the ſentence of excommunication is pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt any, all rights and dutyes both naturall and civill, are to be broken off towards them, and that ſuch as are caſt out, ought by no meanes either actively or paſſively to be communicated withall; ſo that for this cauſe a divorce ought to be made, between Parents &amp; Children, Husband &amp; wife, Brothers &amp; ſiſters, Maſters &amp; ſervants, <hi>Col. Emb. Conf. Men. Jac. Out. Apol.</hi> 10. While they teach, that thoſe which are unequally yoked with unbelievers ought, (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their repentance) by perpetuall excommunication to be ſhut out of the Church, untill the unbelieving party be either converted or dead. <hi>Coll. Embd.</hi> 11. While they imagine that Oaths, ought neither to be taken nor required of any under the New Teſtament. <hi>Coll. Franck. Leeu. and Embd. confeſ. Menn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As concerning the members of the Church in particular,<note place="margin">2. Errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church.</note> the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts</hi> erre, both concerning thoſe which are publique, whether Civill or Eccleſiaſticall, and thoſe wrich are private. 1. Touching the publique Civill perſons. 1. While they teach, that no man un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the New Teſtament, can with a ſafe conſcience exerciſe the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Magiſtrate: and that thoſe things cannot ſtand together to beare the office of a Magiſtrate, and be a member of the true Church. <hi>Coll. Franckend. Embd. confeſ. Menn. Cl. Claeſs.</hi> 2. While they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that the office of the Magiſtrate extends to both tables of the Law. <hi>Coll. Embd. conf. Menn.</hi> 3. While they deny that it is lawfull for a Magiſtrate under the new Teſtament to proclaime or make warre. <hi>Cl. Claeſs. conf. Dordr. confeſ.</hi> 4. While they deny it to be lawfull for the Magiſtrate to puniſh any man with death. For ſay they, as under the Old Teſtament civill puniſhments were inflicted, without the diſcipline of the Church, ſo in the New Teſtament, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall diſcipline ought to have place, not civill puniſhments; for that one kinde of government onely, ought to be practiſed in each. <hi>Joh. Pet. Vand. Meul. in declar.</hi> Much leſſe is it lawfull to inflict capitall puniſhments, either upon a guilty perſon repenting, when he ought to be received into favour, or upon one unrepentant, leaſt it tend to the loſſe of his ſoule. <hi>Menn Sim. and Coll. Wiſ. cum Mior.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning publique Eccleſiaſticall perſons, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre,<note place="margin">3. Errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Church.</note> 1. While they teach, that Miniſters of the word, are not to be brought out of Schooles and Univerſities, or brought up in the ſtudy of the Arts and Sciences. <hi>Coll. Embd. confeſ. Menn.</hi> 2. While
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:113900:22"/>they will have the election and calling of Miniſters of the word, to be in the power of all and ſingular the Members of the Church without exception. <hi>Coll. Embd.</hi> 3. While they take away the equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity as well of the office as authority of Paſtors: and will have Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops ſo diſtinguiſhed from Paſtors and Teachers, that thoſe have the care of divers Churches, yea of an whole Province aſſigned unto them; theſe only of one Congregation; theſe have only power of teaching; thoſe both to teach and adminiſter the Sacraments. <hi>Coll. Embd. Menn. Sins. contra. Mier.</hi> 4. While they deny that the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the word ought to receive a yearly and ſet ſtipend; but onely a contribution for neceſſary uſes as occaſion ſhall require. <hi>Claes. Caeſ. confeſ. Coll. Embd.</hi> 5. While they make the vertue of Gods word, and the Sacraments, to depend upon the worthineſſe of the Miniſters. <hi>Colloq. Emb.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the private members of the Church in ſpecall, the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> erre.<note place="margin">4. Errors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the private mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church.</note> 1. While they teach, that it is unlawfull under the New Teſtament to go to law with others, and to contend before the Magiſtrate. <hi>Coll. Embd. Cl. Claeſ.</hi> 2. That it is unlawfull to beare Armes under the ſame, either defenſive as in watching, or of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive in warre, and either to hire out, or lend our aſſiſtance unto him. <hi>Colloq. Leeu. and Embd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe opinions which we have reckoned up, are maintained by the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> ſome by all of them, ſome by many, ſome by certaine of them: and all which we do not onely thinke to diſcent from the holy Scripture, but to offend moſt grievouſly againſt the Majeſty of God, and his revealed will concerning our faith and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation; yea, amongſt which many are pernitious, and doe alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether exclude from any hope of ſalvation, all thoſe that imbrace them, and continue in the ſame unto the end. Wherefore although the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> may ſeem ſeriouſly to obſerve thoſe things which pertaine to the ſecond table of the law, or the offices of civill and outward charity and juſtice, which we owe unto our neighbour; yea, and that beyond many, which profeſſe the purer Religion: yet ſeeing they tranſgreſſe ſo hainouſly, eſpecially againſt the firſt table of the law; wee hold that they do not onely erre beſide, or about the foundation; but errors which overthrow even the very founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſalvation it ſelfe; and are heartily ſorry that many which ſeeme to be good men, and carefull to lead an honeſt and civill life,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:113900:22"/>ſhould be ſo deceived by a certaine outward vizard of holines, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and modeſty, that they will walke in the way which leadeth unto deſtruction, and renew many Hereſies condemned in the Ancient Church: which that we may not ſeem wrongfully to accuſe them of; we ſhall briefly demonſtrate both.</p>
               <p>That ſuch as profeſſe the doctrines abovementioned,<note place="margin">The foregoing errors do over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> do overthrow the foundation of Salvation, is manifeſt by this. 1. Becauſe they with-draw men, that would be ſaved from the knowledge of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. 2. Becauſe they with-draw them from the knowledge of the Mediator through whom they ſhould be ſaved. 3. Becauſe they with draw them from the knowledge of God, who ſhould ſave them, and to whom they ſhould be brought.</p>
               <p>The firſt head is evident by this; becauſe they deprive a man of the true knowledge of his firſt Eſtate in which he was created;<note place="margin">1. Becauſe they deprive a man of the true knowledge of himſelfe.</note> of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Eſtate, into which he caſt himſelf headlong through ſin; and of his third, unto which he was reſtored. Of the knowledge of his firſt eſtate they deprive a man; while they will not let him acknowledge the benefit which he received from his Creator, either of vertue, that is holines; nor happineſſe following the ſame, that is immortality. The knowledge of his ſecond Eſtate they with-hold from him, while they either deny or extenuate the corruption inherent in him from the beginning, and take away the guilt adherent unto him; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently oppoſe our partaking of the firſt ſin. Likewiſe they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from him, the knowledge of his third eſtate; dividing the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his reparation between God and him; yea aſcribing the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall part thereof unto man; and building his ſalvation upon Gods forcknowledge of his good co-operation began, and continued unto the end: yea putting mans obedience in place of the acceptation of the obedience of his Saviour. VVherefore a man poſſeſſed with this Divinity, can neither know how great is the benefit of nature, which he at firſt received from God: nor how great is the evill both morall, and naturall, which he drew upon himſelf; neither how great, or of what nature is the benefit of grace which was beſtowed upon him from heaven: inſomuch as he can neither humble himſelfe as he ought, nor exalt the goodnes of God.</p>
               <p>The ſecond head appears out of this;<note place="margin">2. They offend againſt the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and office of the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour.</note> becauſe they offend aſwell againſt the perſon and office of the Mediator, as the benefits obtained by him. Againſt his perſon; while they verily overthrow his divine nature; converting the ſame into a nature ſubject to paſſion and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:113900:23"/>death; and his humane nature like unto ours, while they deny that it had the ſame beginning and ſubſtance with ours. His office moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver they corrupt, while they deny thoſe attributes to his Propheticall office which are due unto the ſame, and aſcribe thoſe unto it, which do not agree thereunto, as appears by their Errors above related. So do they corrupt Chriſts prieſtly office, touching the act of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both intenſively and extenſively conſidered. Intenſively, by that very thing denying the truth of his ſufferings, that they contend hee under-went the ſame in his divine nature. Extenſively, by extending the ſame unto innumerable unprofitably, and to no purpoſe. Likewiſe do they corrupt Chriſts benefits both of Juſtification and Sanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as doth appear by what hath been above-ſpoken.</p>
               <p>The third head is evident by this; becauſe they turne the true God into an Idoll.<note place="margin">3. They turn the true God into an Idol.</note> 1. Overthrowing his nature, and in ſtead of one, make three divine Eſſences, diſtant in place one from another. 2. Robbing him of his attributes, by denying partly his infiniteneſſe, partly his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeableneſſe. His infiniteneſſe, while they allow him only omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſence of power, but not of Eſſence: his unchangeableneſſe, as may appear out of their doctrine of the Incarnation and paſſion of Chriſt. 3. Of his operations, reſtraining and cutting ſhort the providence of God; while they teach, that neither are all things actually governed by him: nor that Gods providence doth any thing about evill; nor that men are ſo ſtraitned therby, but that they may go contrary there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and depart from the ſame. By theſe things it is manifeſt that the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> preach another God and another Chriſt, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly another Goſpell; and lay another foundation beſides that which is laid.</p>
               <p>Moreover that they doe reduce many Hereſies which were long ago condemned in the ancient Church,<note place="margin">4. They bring in many here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies long ſince condemned.</note> and again induce them into the chriſtian church, we ſhal now go about to demonſtrate. 1. With the <hi>Manicheans</hi> they inveigh againſt the Old Teſtament, would have it abrogated, and ſtrive that there are things delivered in the Old and New Teſtament contrary to one another. <hi>Epiph. in Panar. her.</hi> Lxvj. Where he obſerveth that the <hi>Manicheans</hi> compared the law and the Prophets to old and withered Trees. How great this Errour is, the ſame <hi>Epiphanius</hi> learns us very well. <hi>Haereſ.</hi> Lxx. Thoſe (ſaith he) which caſt out the Old Teſtament are not any more of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church. 2. With the <hi>Audians,</hi> and <hi>Anthropomorphites,</hi> they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:113900:23"/>will have us ſtick to the letter of the Scripture only. <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> Lxx. 3. With the <hi>Tritheites,</hi> they multiply the divine Eſſence. <hi>Niceph. Lib.</hi> 18. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 49.4. With the <hi>Samoſaſtenians, Photinians,</hi> and <hi>Arrians,</hi> they oppoſe the Deity of the Son of God; while they refer the places which ſpeak of the Unity of Eſſence, of the Perſons of the ſacred Trinity; to unity of will, not of Eſſence, like as the aforeſayd Hereticks contended, ſuch places were to be underſtood of the likenes of Eſſence, not of the Equality. With the <hi>Arrians</hi> alſo they will have the words <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>i. e.</hi> of the ſame Eſſence, hiſſed out, as not being in the Scripture. <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> Lxix. which words were likewiſe had in ſuſpition, by the <hi>Semi-arrians. Haereſ.</hi> 73. With the ſame likewiſe they contend that the Name of the true God is aſcribed to the Father alone: and when as Chriſt cals God the Father, his God, they conclude that he is not equall with God; which to be done like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by the <hi>Arrians, Epi.</hi> teacheth <hi>Haereſ.</hi> Lxix. See alſo <hi>Auguſt. cont. Maxim. &amp; Felician. the Arrians. Tom.</hi> 6. With the ſame alſo they call in queſtion the eternall generation of the Son of God; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider not (as <hi>Epiph.</hi> notes in the ſame place) that God the Father begat the Son after an unſpeakable, incomprehenſible, and moſt holy man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. 5. VVith the <hi>Noetians &amp; Sabellians,</hi> they either deny the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the perſons, or at leaſt-wiſe make it doubtfull. <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> Lvij. &amp; Lxij. To whom <hi>Epiphan</hi> oppoſeth the faith of the Ancient Church. VVe do not ſaith he bring in a plurality of the Godhead, but preach its unity; and while we preach one God, we erre not on the other ſide, but confeſſe the Trinity; Unity in Trinity, and Trinity in Unity; one Godhead of the Father, Sonne, and Holy Ghoſt. 6 With the <hi>Pagans,</hi> and <hi>Manicheans,</hi> they limit God to a certaine place, and deny the infinitenes of the divine Eſſence, including it in the Heaven, or defining it below the ſame. <hi>Damaſ. dial. de haereſ. Manich.</hi> 7. With the <hi>Sabellians,</hi> and <hi>Patripaſſians,</hi> and other Hereticks, they make the unchangeable, and unalterable God, mutable and ſubject to paſſion. <hi>Philaſter. lib. de haereſ. &amp; Rufin. in expoſit. Symb. Apoſt. quae intor opera. Cypr.</hi> So with the <hi>Tropites</hi> they fain that the Word was turned into fleſh. <hi>Philaſtr.</hi> 8. With the <hi>Audians,</hi> and <hi>Anthropomorphites</hi> they op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the inviſibility of God. <hi>Epiph. Aud. Haer.</hi> Lxx. 9. With the <hi>Carpocratians, Appellejans, Valentinians. Apollinariſts,</hi> and <hi>Prodianites,</hi> they deny that the fleſh of Chriſt was made of the ſubſtance of <hi>Mary. Philaſtr. &amp; Epiph. haereſ.</hi> XLIV. 10. With the <hi>Apollinariſts,</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moerites,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:113900:24"/>they defend, that Chriſt verily forſook his divine glory. <hi>Epi. haereſ.</hi> Lxvij. Lxix. <hi>Item,</hi> that the Word was changed into fleſh and bones, and haires, and a whole body, and altered from his own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> 77.11. With the ſame they teach, that Chriſt in his divine nature it ſelf ſuffered his paſſion. <hi>Zozom. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. And that, that which was nailed to the Croſſe, was the very ſubſtance, which was the author of Nature. That thoſe which profeſſe ſuch things ought to be accounted chriſtians. <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> denies, <hi>Epiſt. ad Epict. Corinth. Epiſc. apud Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> Lxvij. 12. With the <hi>Anaſtaſians,</hi> and <hi>Neſtorians</hi> they oppoſe the perſonall union of two natures in Chriſt. <hi>Socra. lib.</hi> 7. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 32. <hi>and Evag. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 11.13. With the <hi>Eutichians,</hi> they deny either the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction of the two natures in Chriſt, or of their Eſſentiall properties, and that Chriſts fleſh is of the ſame ſubſtance with ours. <hi>Evagr. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Niceph. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.14. With the <hi>Apollinariſts,</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine other Hereticks, they deny that Chriſt really took an humane Soul. <hi>Philaſtr. lib. de haereſ. Nicep. lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.15. With the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cionites,</hi> they deny that Chriſt felt in his Soul the wrath of God. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tul. cont. Marcion Ign. Epiſt. ad Tral.</hi> 16. With the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> and <hi>Manicheans</hi> they contend that the New Teſtament was firſt publiſhed by Chriſt, when he was on Earth, and that the commandments of the Two Teſtaments are divers, yea contrary. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> 66. contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>Epiphanius</hi> teacheth in the ſame place, that they make one and the ſame harmony. 17. VVith the <hi>Iews, Cerinthians,</hi> and <hi>Chialiſts,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Hereticks; they feine an Earthly Kingdome of Chriſt, and a Church without calamities. <hi>Inſtin. indial. eum Triph. Iud. Euſeb. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 33. <hi>&amp; Hier. in cap.</hi> 7. <hi>Dan.</hi> 18. VVith the <hi>Sarnoſatenians,</hi> and <hi>Photinians,</hi> they attribute the raiſing up of Chriſt to the power of the Father only. <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> 65. <hi>&amp;</hi> 71.19. With the <hi>Apellejans,</hi> and <hi>Origenians,</hi> they ſpeak doubtfully of the Reſurrection. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> 44. <hi>&amp;</hi> 64. 20. With the <hi>Cathariſts, Novatians, &amp; Donatiſts,</hi> they conſtitute the Church only of perfect ones, and corrupt the exerciſe of the diſcipline of the Church, by too much ſeverity towards thoſe that are falne. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> Lxix. 21. With the <hi>Manicheans,</hi> they convert the Sacraments into bare ſigns, and leſſen the neceſſity of them. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> Lxvj. 22. VVith the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> they make the worthineſſe of the Sacraments to depend upon the holines of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters that adminiſter them. <hi>Aug. Tom.</hi> 7. <hi>cont. Creſc. &amp; Gaudent. item
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:113900:24"/>cont. Lit. Petil. &amp; in Epiſt. paſſim.</hi> 23. VVith the ſame and the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians, Marcionites, Eunomians, Montaniſts,</hi> and divers other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks; they repeat Baptiſme, adminiſtred out of their congregations. <hi>Ibid. &amp; Epiph. haereſ.</hi> xlij. <hi>&amp; Epoſit. Cath. Fid. Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>Zozom. hiſt. Eccl. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 26. <hi>&amp; Philaſt. lib. de haereſ.</hi> 24. VVith the <hi>Donariſts, Euno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mians,</hi> and other Hereticks they condemn childrens baptiſme. <hi>Aug. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cont. Donat. cap.</hi> 23.24.25 <hi>&amp; Concil. Milev. can.</hi> 11.25. VVith the <hi>Cathariſts, &amp; Donatiſts,</hi> they will not have the Lords Supper ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred, unleſſe to pure and perfect ones. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> 59.26. with the <hi>Nicolaites, Baſilidians, &amp; Carpocratians,</hi> ſome of the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> teach both communion of wives, and goods, others this latter onely. <hi>Epiph. haereſ.</hi> xxiv. &amp; xxvij. 27. VVith thoſe of whom <hi>Iude</hi> ſpeaks, verſ. 8. and other unruly, they ſpeak evill of Governments. 28. with the <hi>Cataphrygians, &amp; Gnosticks,</hi> they boaſt of prophets, dreames, and viſions. <hi>Phil. lib. de haereſ.</hi> 29. VVith the <hi>Pelagians, Semipelagians, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinians. Papiſts, &amp; Arminians,</hi> they erre moſt of their other errors, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the threefold eſtate of man, of integrity, corruption, &amp; reſtaurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and either extenuate or pervert the benefit of originall righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, blemiſh of corruption, grace of reſtitution, and the benefits fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the ſame, as by comparing the Articles above mentioned, with the doctrine of the other Hereticks, may appeare.</p>
               <p>It it evident moreover, that the enemy of mankind hath laboured by <hi>Anabaptiſme;</hi> that the order both of Church and ſtate, being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown, or at leaſtwiſe diſturbed and brought into contempt, the good government of chriſtian Churches and common-wealths might fall to the ground. From hence came it, that the authority of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call order was weakned by the licentiouſneſſe of <hi>Enthuſiaſts,</hi> venting their own dreams and inventions: and the choice of thoſe, who ſhould attend the holy things, committed to the rude multitude; the ſacred keyes alſo, which ought to be born by the repreſentative church, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the pleaſure of every one, and ſo a kind of Anarchy &amp; intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſorder brought into the Houſe of God. With how many, and how lamentable tumults common-wealths have been ſhaken, ſince this kind of doctrin began to be ſpread and practiſed, the records both of high &amp; <hi>Lower Germany</hi> do teſtifie; which could not be extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or quieted without a great deal of blood. How much alſo they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the authority of the Magiſtrate, and how much they leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen his dignity, appears both out of their Tenets, and the practice of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:113900:25"/>the <hi>Muntzerians,</hi> thoſe of <hi>Miniſter,</hi> and others of that kind. And indeed how is it poſſible, that the Magiſtrate, can preſerve his honour and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nown with the common people, when they ſhall weigh theſe Apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſmes in their mind. That he which exerciſeth the office of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate cannot be a member of the Apoſtolike Church. <hi>Colloq. Franck.</hi> That Chriſt hath forbidden all his, to have any civill goverment. That in the New Teſtament there is no place for the office of a civill Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate. <hi>Cl. Claeſs. confeſs. Mennon.</hi> That tis doubtfull, whether a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate can be ſaved. <hi>Colloq. Embd.</hi> That chriſtians are not oblieged to give their oath to the Magiſtrate. <hi>Coll. Embd.</hi> As neither to beare Arms, or keep watch, when we are invaded by the Enemy. <hi>ibid.</hi> which how perillous and deſtructive it is to common-wealths, needs not to be ſhewed. For neither can any thing be more powerfull to expoſe both publike and private eſtate, to the Tyrany of an Enemy, and to turn all things upſide down, then when this bewitching, coloured o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver with a fair ſhew of Religion and piety, hath poſſeſſed the minds of men; and tis held not only indifferent, but even unlawfull to reſiſt an Enemy that invades our countrey. VVhich opinion, leaſt it ſhould ſeem now to be aboliſhed, and grown out of date, was confirmed by a late and notable example, of the <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> which heretofore had their habitation in the country of <hi>Zurich.</hi> For when a few yeers ſince, the <hi>German,</hi> &amp; <hi>Rhetian</hi> war waxing hot, no ſmall danger ſeemed to threaten reformed <hi>Helvetia,</hi> and eſpecially the Territory of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth of <hi>Zurich;</hi> it ſeemed good to the honourable Magiſtrate, to ordain the uſuall muſters, and viewing of Arms. The <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> being called to theſe exerciſes, they began, not only to refuſe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the command; but alſo to inculcate into others, that war was ſent from God being offended as a puniſhment. That a Kingdome was not defended by Arms, but amendment of our manners; That it was not lawfull for a chriſtian to bear Arms, nor to be armed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his country. With which divinity, &amp; other the like precepts, ſome being infected; they thought that they muſt rather forſake, country, wives, children, fortunes, and all things whatſoever; then by moſt juſt Arms, to drive the Enemy out of their country. The religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Magiſtrate of <hi>Zurich</hi> uſed all means to informe and inſtruct theſe men, and to recall them to their duty; ſearching out, and confuting at large all things wherewith they profeſſed they were troubled; ſo as he left them no cauſe of any more ſcruple. Men choſen out of both
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:113900:25"/>orders, civill and Eccleſiaſticall, eminent for prudence and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence conferre with them; and take very good heed, that nothing fall from them which might carry any ſhew of cavillation, or more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent proceeding But ſo far were they from departing from their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid aſſertions, that being demanded whether he that beareth the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Magiſtrate, and in the ſame believeth and liveth as a chriſtian ought, could be ſaved? they would not aſſent. There are propoſed to them moſt eaſie conditions. That they ſhould be freed from the uſuall form of an oath, &amp; the Magiſtrate would be content with their ſimple promiſe in giving their faith; that they ſhould be releaſed from the uſe of Arms; if they would but aſſiſt their country, with prayers, good wiſhes, and ſuch other godly waies and means. They ſhould indeed be oblieged to come to the Sermons, yet with this condition, that they ſhould freely teſtifie their diſſent from any thing delivered, either to the Paſtors, or other officers of the Church: and for any thing elſe, they might promiſe themſelves all favour, courteſie, and protection, from the Magiſtrate. When neither this gentleneſſe of the Senate of <hi>Zurich,</hi> was able to overcome or aſſwage the minds of theſe obſtinate men; they are deſired, of their owne accord, to depart ſome other where, that neither by their doctrine nor example, the ſafety of their Country might be indangered; and leave was given them to take all ſuch things with them, as ſhould be neceſſary for their ſuſtentation. But if they would not have ſome of their wives and children (free from their errours) to go out of the country, they ſhould leave for them an equall portion of their Eſtate to the adminiſtration of ſome Citizens, which either they themſelves ſhould chuſe, or whom the Magiſtrate ſhould judge faithfull; leaſt the departure of ſome, might be to the damage of others of theirs, or to the burthen of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth; That all things ſhould be faithfully adminiſtred; yea, reſtored unto them again, it ſo be, they returned to a better mind. When this was likewiſe in vaine propounded unto theſe ſtubborne men; they are condemned to beare part of the publike expences, which they had been the cauſe of, and ſome fines are laid upon them, although ſmall and very tollerable. But it is not to be ſaid, how much they began to abuſe this mildnes of the Magiſtrate, to withdraw their obedience accuſe the Magiſtrate of Tyranny, and heape calumnies and reproaches upon him. At length the patience of the Senate being quite overcome, leaſt this ſtubbornnes ſhould be turned into an example of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:113900:26"/>licentiouſneſſe, and rebellion; it was decreed that the goods of theſe obſtinate men ſhould be forfeited to the Common-wealth. This drew not only murmuring and complaints from them; but even made ſome of them in the mind to trouble the publike peace, and by night meetings to ſtirre up tumults; yea to that height of impiety, did their obſtinateneſſe proceed, that they expreſly prayed unto God that he would by plague, famine, and other ſuch like generall calamities, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine the rage of the Magiſtrate, whom they ſo moſt unjuſtly accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Which hardning in their evill, conſtrained the Magiſtrate to this, though unwilling, that he clapt ſome of the rebels, who were moſt unruly into priſon; yet allowing them ſufficient liberty. Vpon which occaſion, they were divers times dealt with, both by principall men of the Magiſtracy and likewiſe by divers other faithfull ſervants of God, learned and reverend men; that they ſhould caſt downe thoſe proud ſtomackes, and conſider ſeriouſly of their owne and their Countreys ſafety; but there could nothing be gotten from them, but preſumptuous and crooked anſwers, and cunning equivocations: yea, by ſecret practiſes they came to this, that by the uſe of falſe keyes, they brake out of the Priſon, and got themſelves out of the power of the Magiſtrate. Being taken againe, and now kept ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſtraighter, (yet ſtill having much liberty) as being put into a ſpacious and pleaſant Monaſtery, they are ſet to handy-workes, the richer are bidden to provide for themſelves, the reſt are taken care for, by the liberality of the Senate; yet being weary of this reſtraint alſo, they bring their keepers aſleep by unlawfull meanes, brake thorow the wall, and about midnight of the next day after Eaſter, in the yeare 1636. violating even the ſafety of the walls; they eſcape all out, ſaving ſome few. And though it was hoped, that they would at leaſt wiſe get them out of the Countrey of <hi>Zurich:</hi> notwithſtanding they returne againe, and fall to making ſtirres and tumults, with as much perverſeneſſe as before. Neither yet was there any greater puniſhment laid upon them; the Senate thinking rather by their mildneſſe to overcome the wickedneſſe of th<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe men; ſo that beſides cloſer impriſonment nothing more was done unto them. Nor were the Miniſters of the word wanting to do any thing they could, but by inſtructions, admonitions, intreaties, carefully indeavored, either to make them leave their errors and ſtubbornneſſe, or elſe to depart out of the Country ſome other where. They urged nothing
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:113900:26"/>but liberty, and proteſt that the faithfull ought not to plead their cauſe in Bands, and in them to render a reaſon of their faith. And although they ſeemed to require a conference, nevertheleſſe all things being offered them, that ſeemed requiſite to a lawfull diſputation, they at length deceived the hopes and wiſhes of all; and againe breaking out of the Priſon, in which they were detained; eſcaped away all, excepting three or foure; which could not follow the reſt. Of whom, two bound themſelves with a moſt unheard of Vow, that they would never doe any more worke, nor taſte a bit of meat, nor drop of drink. And which is moſt wonderfull, one of them was ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate that he ſtarved himſelf to death: by whoſe example the other being terrified, he followed better counſell. Which obſtinacy of mind is ſo much the more execrable, for that theſe men might every hour have obtained their liberty, if they would but only have promiſed the Magiſtrate to have departed out of the Country of <hi>Zurich.</hi> Thoſe of them that got out of that Territory ſtaying a good while upon the borders of their Country, and heaping up reproaches upon the moſt patient Magiſtrate, doubted not to accuſe him unto forreiners of moſt unheard of crueltie; when he notwithſtanding, although he had found the Ring-leaders of them guilty of moſt hainous offences, which any other of the Citizens had publiquely ſuffered for; would at no hand, ſhew any example of ſeverity towards thoſe kinde of men; leaſt it ſhould be imputed rather to the hatred of the Sect, then to the crimes of the Sectaries. Yet ſome of theſe men would rather go over to the Papiſts, and joyne themſelves unto Idolatrous aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, then be accounted amongſt the Orthodox. All which being written out of the publique Records, and by me faithfully related, I thought fit here to inſert, that I might give a character of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists,</hi> and that the patience of the Orthodox Magiſtrate of <hi>Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich</hi> towards the ſeducers and ſeduced might hence appeare. The whole Hiſtory of this buſineſſe is contained in an Epiſtle of a learned and grave divine, to a worthy and reverend Paſtor of the French Church at <hi>Amſterdam.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of all that hath been ſaid, it is evident,<note place="margin">Aplication of all.</note> how needfull it is both for the Church and Common-Wealth, to joyne the labour of the Univerſities, with that of the Church for the confutation of the <hi>Anabaptiſts;</hi> and with united hearts and hands, indeavour to h<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this doctrine, which brings ſo certaine deſtruction to Church,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:113900:27"/>Common-Wealth, and our own ſouls: both that the conſciences as yet addicted to the truth, may not be drawne unto deceit and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, by their faire ſhews, and counterfeit vizard of innocence, holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſimplicity; and that thoſe who have hitherto beene decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, either by the flattery of the Sectaries, or the whited face of the Sect, may be ſtirred up in the feare of the Lord, to take this matter into ſerious meditation; and conſider with themſelves, how many horrible and pernicious Tenets, and how hurtfull both to publique and private quietneſſe, lye hidden as it were behinde a curtaine, under this ſimple name of <hi>Anabaptists.</hi> To whom we wiſh from the Lord with all our hearts, the knowledge, love, and practice of that truth which by the ſpeciall grace of God is preſerved in the Orthodox Churches; and therewithall both preſent and perpetuall happineſſe. Neither doe we go about to ſtir up the Magiſtrate againſt thoſe men; nor would we have any force offered to their conſciences; but thinke thoſe meanes onely ought to be uſed, which may conduce to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of thoſe that erre, the reproving of their errors, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the truth, ſo farre as it may ſtand with Chriſtian pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and charity.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
